<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nevv world, or, the nevv reformed church. Discovered out of the second epistle of Peter the third chap verse 13. First opened briefly, and some points pourtrayed and propounded before some of the nobilitie and others in the country. Afterwards more fully delineated, and prosecuted before the Honorable House of Parliament; May 30. An. Dom. 1641. And upon the request of some of them, desiring coppies, was limbed up for the presse, according to the maine parts then, and there delivered. / By Nath. Homes Dr. in D.</title>
            <author>Homes, Nathanael, 1599-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 203 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86501</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E171_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8246</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873254</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873254</idno>
            <idno type="VID">157041</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86501)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 157041)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 30:E171[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nevv world, or, the nevv reformed church. Discovered out of the second epistle of Peter the third chap verse 13. First opened briefly, and some points pourtrayed and propounded before some of the nobilitie and others in the country. Afterwards more fully delineated, and prosecuted before the Honorable House of Parliament; May 30. An. Dom. 1641. And upon the request of some of them, desiring coppies, was limbed up for the presse, according to the maine parts then, and there delivered. / By Nath. Homes Dr. in D.</title>
                  <author>Homes, Nathanael, 1599-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 79 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. P. and M. S. for William Adderton, and are to be sold at his shop in Duck-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 2nd, III, 13 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Puritans --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:157041:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:157041:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NEVV WORLD, OR THE NEVV REFORMED CHVRCH.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Diſcovered out of the ſecond Epiſtle of</hi> Peter <hi>the third chap verſe 13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Nevertheleſſe we according to his prom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe looke for new Heavens, and a new Earth, wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> righteouſneſſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Firſt opened briefly, and ſome points pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed and propounded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fore ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Nobilitie and others in the Country.</p>
            <p>Afterwards more fully delineated, and proſecuted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Honorable Houſe of PARLIAMENT; <hi>May</hi> 30. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1641.</p>
            <p>And upon the requeſt of ſome of them, deſiring Cop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pies, was limbed up for the preſſe according to the maine parts then, and there delivered.</p>
            <p>By NATH. HOMES Dr. in D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. P.</hi> and <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>William Adderton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Duck-lane.</hi> 1641.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:157041:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:157041:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE THE KNIGHTS, AND BVRGESSES, OF THE HOVSE OF COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONS ASSEMBDED IN <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthies of Iſrael,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this <hi>extreame</hi> age (for this laſt is moſtly upon extreames) if I ſhould write nothing but a Title of dedication (as they call it) J ſhould ſeeme Cynically to neglect.<note place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mios in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Heſiod.</note> If J ſhould inlarge the Phylacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, or Panegyrick of uſuall prefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, J ſhould be thought Phariſaicall, or Paraſitiscall. If I ſhould relate what relations have been between ſome of you and this <hi>Embryon</hi> of thoughts, to quicken it to that it is now growne, J might be deemed here impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, &amp; unſeaſonable if not impertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Or if I ſhould take upon me now to implore your forward ſpirits to doe any thing for the Church or State, I ſhould but anticipate the booke it ſelfe. Therefore J ſhall onely ſpend ſo much time, paper and words as to aſſure you, that in and from my best intentions, and affections this diſcourſe is yours, my prayers yours; and what by my utmoſt abilities, and endavours J may doe for you, in the Lord is alſo yours. Your acceptance is onely to reade that, and to beleeve
<pb facs="tcp:157041:3"/>this. I know truth will maintaine it ſelfe. The Lord hath made it a God on earth. <hi>Magna eſt veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, &amp; praevalebit.</hi> But ſomtimes her ſpeaker is malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.16.</note> for her ſake; though an Apoſtle. The ungram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar'd world will pinch on the moode and tenſe, when they cannot gaine ſay the ſence. Jf the ſermon was preached for your ſake, and the world prate againſt mee for the Sermons ſake, I hope you will looke upon mee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and candid in my intentions, for the ſame reaſon Solomon favored <hi>Abiathar</hi> that was really in fault.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hortis vir.</note> Hee forbare to puniſh him as he deſerved, <hi>becauſe</hi> (ſaith heto him) <hi>thou beareſt the arke of the Lord God before</hi> David <hi>my father, and becauſe thou haſt beene afflicted in all wherein my father was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted.</hi> J minde my promiſe of brevitie. Therefore for cloſe.</p>
            <p>The ſweet God of heaven bleſſe his Majeſtie, the true nobly Nobles and you worthies in this our Iſrael for that great good you have done; and the ſame God proſper you, that <hi>the wine of the Churches through refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation kept to the laſt, may prove the beſt,</hi> to the increaſe of the Churches joy of feaſting, bere with her Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iohn 2. Prov. 9.1, 2, 3, 4.5. Iſa. 25.6. Mat. 22.4.</note> in his pure ordinances; Is the earneſt prayer of him that is intirely yours in the Lord with all humbleneſſe,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>NATH. HOMES.</signed>
               <dateline>From his unworthy obſcure study. <date>
                     <hi>Aguſt 4. 1641.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:157041:3"/>
            <head>THE NEVV REFORMED CHVRCH.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Epiſt. of PET. 3. cap. verſe 13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Nevertheleſſe we according to his promiſe looke for new heavens, and a new earth, wherein dwelleth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat your thoughts may goe <hi>Logically</hi> downe with me to my Text, I ſhall give but a word, but point with the finger, to intimate the way of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles method, viz. his ſcope being to cure the immorality of the laſt times, he goes the <hi>Paracelſian</hi> way of Phyſicke. That is to apply hot remedies, to hot diſeaſes. The diſeaſes of the laſt times,<note place="margin">Verſe 3.</note> being ſcoffing and jearing at the laſt times, the common walking fire, or ſquib-guns of Hell-Zelotes to flare and flaſh in the face of truth, and honeſty. The Apoſtle applies this hot operating <hi>doſis.</hi> That as ſure as the Lord would haſten the laſt day, ſo would hee make it an hot day: as much hotter then the day of judging the old world, as fire would bee hotter then thoſe waters, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. to the end of the 10.</p>
            <p>This therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, ſhould awaken men.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:157041:4"/>before it come. The conſideration, before the execution, as the dawning before the ſunne-riſing; and put men firſt upon a converſation of piety, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. And ſo ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, upon an expectation of eveilaſting felicitie, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>Yet ſo (ſaith the Apoſtle) as we doe not looke over, or beyond that wee are to looke for, before that great day, namely new Heavens, &amp;c. And therefore the Apoſtle, like a Cautioniſt brings in the word with a Nevertheleſſe. Nevertheleſſe, we according to his promiſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>You perceive already (I beleeve) that in the firſt word, there is juſt occaſion given, not to ſlight the very <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall</hi> expreſſion of the holy Ghoſt in my text. As that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Greeke, (to which the <hi>Syr.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> directly anſwers) ſignifies either Nevertheleſſe, as in our new tranſlation, or an adverſative,<note place="margin">High Dutch, <hi>Aber.</hi> So alſo <hi>Arius Montan.</hi>
               </note> or diverſative <hi>But,</hi> as in the old tranſlatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and in the tranſlations of other Churches in their native language. The learned Tranſlators therefore in our laſt tranſlatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaw ſome emphaticall thing in this ſmall title <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that they drewit out into ſuch a length; and perceived no doubt as wee conceive &amp; receive the Apoſtle; that if he had here meant the ſame materiall Heavens, as in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer verſes, he would have ſaid, <hi>And</hi> we expect, and not have uſed ſuch an exceptive, or a word ſo commonly, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred exceptively, &amp; adverſatively, as therby to glance our expectation to an heaven upon earth before the Churches arivall at the Heavens above the earth. And that with a beleeving expectation or hope (as the word in the original ſignifies) and not a conjecturall,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> or of bare opinion; So that the bleſſed Apoſtle in his illation of this verſe ſeemes to uſe a kind of <hi>Rhetoricall Epanorthoſis,</hi> or correction of himſelfe; <q>thus, ſay I the heavens ſhall bee diſſolved? <hi>Nevertheleſſe,</hi> ſo underſtand me, as that I ſtill meane we ſhall have <hi>now heavens, &amp;c. here.</hi>
               </q> And becauſe naturally mens thoughts are very flat, and their affections dull touching this heaven upon earth, therefore the holy Ghoſt uſeth other flowers of eloquence to dreſſe forth and adorne this glorious eſtate of the reformed Church. Firſt, <hi>a metaphor,</hi> comparing it to Heaven; the beſt conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:157041:4"/>that is, becauſe the Churches reformation hath its o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nall thence, and its end of perfection there. And meane while hath the ſpeciall preſence of God there, which is the very forme of heaven.<note place="margin">Some of the pious Fathers.</note> In ſo much as in that reſpect ſome of the Ancients ſaid, Heaven was a qualitie, rather then a place.</p>
            <p>Secondly, and <hi>Hyperbole,</hi> or high ſounding expreſſion of the newneſſe, or newalty of this ſtate of the Church; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it a <hi>new</hi> heavens &amp; a <hi>new</hi> earth, as if of another ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance (for ſo <hi>new</hi> imports) of a new ſubſtance. Howbeit the Apoſtle only meanes, <hi>new</hi> in accidents, in qualities, &amp; circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarces. Yet ſo he ſpeakes to draw on our minds to reach home to a right opinion of thoſe <hi>new</hi> heavens, &amp;c. That there ſhall be ſuch a <hi>renewed</hi> condition of the Church, as if it were a <hi>new</hi> one. The like expreſſion the Apoſtle uſeth in deſcribing the righteous condition of the renewed Church ſaying, that therein ſhall <hi>dwell righteouſneſſe,</hi> putting the <hi>Abſtract,</hi> for the <hi>Concret, Righteouſneſſe,</hi> for righteous men, a righteous people. For no men or people can be purely righteous in this life. That is the prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, and incommunicable difference of Heaven pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, for a full evidence what is the meaning of this text, let us conſider it <hi>Theologically</hi> in the Divinity of it. <hi>Nevertheleſſe</hi> is a diſtinctive particle: firſt, of a new Heaven on Earth, from that above ſecondly, of the Saints hopes from the worlds. As for <hi>Heavens</hi> and new <hi>Earth;</hi> Some looking on theſe words curſoryly,<note place="margin">A lapide.</note> and with an ordinary eye, have runne away with a confidence that they are to be underſtood of the Heaven of Heavens, and the eternall glory of the Saints there. But theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretors are heavenly wide. For this interpretation is too ſpirituall. For beſides what we ſaid in the Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall conſideration.</p>
            <p>Note here firſt, what neede was there of this commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datorie information of the glorious eſtate of Heaven, which is glimmering in the darke minds of heathens, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe their diſcourſes of the <hi>Elyſian</hi> fields, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:157041:5"/>immortality of the ſoule; much more doth it glare in the inlightned minds of the Saints. Laſt of all was there any neede to tell the Saints that in Heaven above dwells righteouſneſſe. Secondly, how or wherein might the Prophets and Apoſtles meane that the heavens of the bleſſed were new, more to the Saints in their ages then to the reſt of all the Saints, who by a continued howerly ſuceſſion, in one place or another are going to the ſame? Thirdly, If Heaven here ſignifies the ſtate of glory, what ſhall wee doe with, or what ſhall wee make of the new earth? Fourthly, if the new heavens here meant, are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed new heavens, and with knowne promiſes, and in all ages the ableſt of Gods Church could never parallel to this text any other places then <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.22. as precedent promiſes. And <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.1. Asuttered by S. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apoſtle, who was Co-Apoſtle, and Coeve of the ſame time with Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> though the time of writing may ſomewhat differ; how ſhall we wreſt thoſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to meane the heavens of glory? for no violence can doe it, without many manifeſt contradictions.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Other Divines commonly called the <hi>Chiliaſts,</hi> or <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenaries,</hi> would (as their names import) underſtand this text, of the Martyres reigning a thouſand yeares on earth as in a particular ſpeciall heaven upon earth, peculiar to them, before they be taken up, ſoule and body into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven above. But theſe are as wide on the other ſide, and that as farre as earth from heaven, of innumerable parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars that might be alleadged, let us at this time bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with a few touches. Firſt, for that leading place (as they account it) <hi>Revel.</hi> 20.4, &amp;c. let us goe no further then the expreſſe text, and thus farre it acquites it ſelfe; Firſt that the text ſpeakes of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>That the ſoules of them (whoſe bodies had beene ſmitten or be headed with the axe) not their bodies too, ſhould reigns theſe</hi> 1000. <hi>yeares.</hi>   And although ſoules oft times in the Scripture do ſignifie the whole perſons, ſoules and body conjunct; yet ſoules cannot ſo ſignifie here, becauſe the holy Ghoſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely and emphatically prevents this by telling us that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:157041:5"/>the axe, or ſome ſuch mortall engine of Martyr-dome had diſtinguiſhed the ſoule from the body as farre as Heaven from Earth. The holy Ghoſt intending here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, to comfort herein the Church on earth touching thoſe bleeding members. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>  That howſoever to the ſenſes, &amp; opinion of the world, theſe ſlame Saints may ſeeme to periſh, yet as their bodies are aſleepe in the earth, ſo their ſoules for each moment of Martyrdom and bodily death have 1000. yeares reigning. <hi>i. e.</hi> an eternity of felicity in Heaven, or their ſoules have many yeares felicitie in Heaven till God ſet their heads on their ſhoulders againe, and rev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ite their bodies to their ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Secondly; it is not in the text <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they roſe againe, or lived againe (which would have ſomewhat ſounded of a reſurrection of their whole perſon:) But it is only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> They thoſe ſoules lived in Heaven.   And although there be in the next verſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they lived againe,   yet it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a contrarie ſort of people, and about a contrary bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe. Namely, that the wicked unregenerated world, the meane while had not ſo much as attained to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>living againe</hi> by regeneration in the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> ſince their death in lapſed firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> in whom ſtanding in innocency they were alive. And ſo ſaith the text expreſſely, for the thouſand yeares,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pareus,</hi> on <hi>Revel. Haee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinio eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traſidem co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thalicam.</hi> Ioh. 5.28.29. Let him that wil be ſatisfied in this poine reade that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Pareus</hi> on <hi>Apoc.</hi> 20. where beſides his c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he hath exquiſite tracts and particular diſputes of the point.</note> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> the long time the Martyres ſoules had beene, and ſhould be in Heaven, even afore the generall reſurrection; the wicked ſo ill thrift all this time on earth under the meanes of grace that they attaine not to the firſt <hi>reſurrection,</hi> the firſt degree of life eternall to live by converſion. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> This opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Chiliaſme, ſaith a moſt grave learned, &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally approved Divine, as moſt hath beene in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is contrary to the generall and univerſall faith and beliefe, profeſſed by the Church, in <hi>John</hi> 5.28.29. as hee quotes the place. And therefore it made the Church of God along time to doubt of the authority and authentie of the books of the <hi>Revelation.</hi> Even ſo long as unskilfull interpr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tours wreſted it to this opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>  We are not deſirous to conceale that many of the more
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:157041:6"/>pious and learned Fathers were led away with that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> But then let us have leave to note the levitie of the cauſe, and the ignominie of the event.   The cauſe was a meere credulouſneſſe of the later, believing the report and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the former. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> believes <hi>Victorinus Picta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ienſis.</hi> He <hi>Dyoniſius Alexandrinus.</hi> He <hi>Hepos Epiſcopus Egypti.</hi> He <hi>Tertullianus.</hi> He <hi>Irenaus.</hi> He <hi>Juſtin Martyr.</hi> (at leſt theſe were the men if the order not ſo exact, that handed this tradition from one to another.) And the laſt man on whoſe ſleeve they all hang the chiefe of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe in this point (as <hi>Irenaus</hi> confeſſeth) was <hi>Papias,</hi> whom they conceived to have beene Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> hearer. And ſo (as they intimate) knew Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> minde and meaning to leane that way. But as the text in that 21 of <hi>Revelat.</hi> ſhewes that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> did not ſo meane; ſo <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias</hi> was not a hearer, or ſeer of any of the Apoſtles, and therefore not of Saint <hi>Iohn:</hi> So hee confeſſeth himſelfe,<note place="margin">In exo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Sui. operis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>And for the ignominie that that opinion drew on it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> Hiſt. cap <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Papius</hi> the firſt Authour of that opinion was a credulous man, and apt to receive fables for verities.</q> So hee; Therefore Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> juſtly confuted him, and his followers. And ſo in allages following their times are recorded in the moſt judicious and pious eccleſiaſticall writers moſt juſtly confuted as guilty of a groſſe error in that reſpect.<note place="margin">To ſsan. Cenſ. patram. Fox. Act. and Mon.</note> And for mine owne part, I ſee not <hi>Cui bono,</hi> to what end any ſhould bee zealous for the opinion. I would willingly know of the late Arminian ſect, why they are ſo hot for it? And of thoſe Anti-Arminian orthodoxe, that ſeeme to hearken this way whether this Tenet may not dazle their ſight from ſeeing and looking after that more generall reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Church of Gods pious ones, whiles they ſtare ſo after a ſurmiſed &amp; imagined comfort of the ſmall handfull of Axe-hewen, or bloodſhed martyrs. And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till then that I receive that ſatisfaction, and an anſwer to other doubts, I ſhall deſire by the leave of charitie to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:157041:6"/>hold where I am againſt Chiliaſme, with modeſtie.</p>
            <p>As for this text of <hi>Peter</hi> it ſeemes farre enough from that opinion. Firſt, becauſe Heaven and Earth are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly named and heaven before earth, as the chiefe of that newneſſe here meant. Secondly, this newneſſe was firſt in theſe expreſſe termes primarily propheſied to the Jewes (though participatively to the Gentiles,) and that after <hi>Iſaiah</hi> had propheſied, their captivity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. view the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the method of the chapter, how Iewes and Gentiles are put together to receive theſe promiſes; but the Iewes are put firſt, and as the principall, the Gentiles as acceſſory part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> ſhould ſeeme as a comfort to them. And to them now ſcattered, and to the ſame purpoſe, mentioned againe by Saint <hi>Peter</hi> here. But if this new heavens, &amp;c. ſhould bee promiſed onely to Martyrs reſiſting to blood from how narrow and particular, and ſad a Topick place or argument would theſe intended comforts bee drawne. For wee ſee how few or none of the Jewes have beene Martyrs hitherto, and how forlorne their condition hath beene, and ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to here of greater miſerie, as a way to ſo ſhort and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular a comfort, with the reſtored Church of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, in that kind.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt therefore fly in the middle Region, goe in the middle path. <hi>Medio tutiſsimus ibis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We therefore by new Heavens, and a new earth, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>a new forme of worſhip;</hi> religion in the expreſſion thereof reformed, brought more cloſe to the rule of the Goſpel, made more ſpirituall, and <hi>heaven like;</hi> and <hi>earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> men made new, changed, turned into new creatures by the power of Religion ſo reformed. And thus in divers places heaven ſignifies religion, and earth, the perſons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligioniſed. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. oft. Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> oft, chap. 1. verſ. 3. chap. 2. verſ. 6. chap. 3. verſ. 10. chap. 6.12. Becauſe the externall worſhip is a type of heaven, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. verſ. 26, 27. <hi>Hagg.</hi> 2.6. In which two laſt places, where it is ſaid, God ſhooke once, and would ſhake againe heaven and earth; the Lord al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes to mount <hi>Sina,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 19.16.</note> that thereby thunder and lightning and earthquake, hee ſhooke the heavens materiall; and ſpirituall, the law, and tables when he delivered them, and the earth, materiall, and metonimicall or metaphoricall,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:157041:7"/>the men, <hi>Moſes</hi> and the reſt trembled, and ſo at the giving of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.18. to 28.</note> by the ſufferings of Chriſt, the heavens and the earth ſeemed to be moved. The Sunne eclipſed, the earth trembled, the heavenly temple rent, the beholders quaked: And at the giving of the ſpirit for extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie gifts as ſeales of the Goſpel, there was a ſhaking of one of the lower heavens, the ayre (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calles it an heaven) by reaſon of a mighty wind. So that this ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſignifies all one with making, and creating new hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, &amp;c. And to doe this <hi>according to his foregoing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> is to doe it according to <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.22. and <hi>Hagg.</hi> 2.6. <hi>In the expectation of which</hi> Saint <hi>Paul. Heb.</hi> throughout the Epiſtle. And Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> throughout the booke of the <hi>Revelation</hi> joyne for this <hi>new</hi> ſtate of the Church, being then but begun, and in part, and here and there but in a few particular places in compariſon of what ſhould be for future, when Jewes and Gentiles ſhould both come in; and in regard that this begunne new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſoone ſuffered much eclipſe and interception, o're it ſhould for future, therefore the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles looked beyond that to a future per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> that ſhall inhabit in this new eſtate of religion and men, it is queſtioned by ſome, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt as more promulgated, or the righteouſneſſe of men, as more practiſed bee here meant? But the rules in ſubordinate things are not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: therefore nothing hinders but both are here meant. And by reaſon of their Connection muſt be.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Its here meant that Chriſts righteouſneſſe ſhall bee more revealed unto men, and into men. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. And Chriſt being made unto them righteouſneſſe, hee ſhall alſo bee made unto them wiſedome, ſanctification, and redemption, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. For when the grace of the Goſpel appeares not onely unto men, but into men, <hi>it teacheth them to deny all ungodlineſſe, and to live godly righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, &amp;c. Tit.</hi> 2.12. And theſe righteouſneſſe, or righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſes in the deſcent, ſhall be a towne dweller, a free
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:157041:7"/>Deniſon of this new world, and its kingdomes. A free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, in feeſimple.</p>
            <p>The text being thus opened, you may perceive the ſumme of it to be a divine Coſmography, or a divine deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription of a ſpirituall new world.</p>
            <p>In particular, wee may note firſt, the Antipodes, the contraries to the inhabitants of the Eden, or more glorious tract of this new world: And theſe are pointed at in the <hi>Nevertheleſſe.</hi> What ever the world thinke, whether ſcoffe, or not ſcoffe. Have a vaine hope or no hope; or what ever meere good ſtates men, or generall honeſt minded men, touching only an heaven above. Yet <hi>We: Nevertheleſſe we looke for, &amp;c.</hi> So that this antitheſis diſtinguiſheth theſe diſcoverers of the new world from their hope, and the object thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Hemiſphere of the new found land of this new world. And that
<list>
                  <item>1. By the ſubſtance
<list>
                        <item>Heaven.</item>
                        <item>Earth.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. By the Accidents or qualities, or properties of both.
<list>
                        <item>1. The Noveltie or newneſſe.</item>
                        <item>2. The Equitie or righteouſneſſe.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>So that as in the morning you heard handled by my predeceſſor, the <hi>Architectonica;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Out of 1 <hi>Chron</hi> 28.10 By Mr. <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds.</hi>
               </note> the building of the new houſe of the reformed Church. So now I am to preſent you with a map of the <hi>Coſmographie,</hi> or diſcription of the new world of the Church.</p>
            <p>A Map. I ſay, one map (not ſeverall particular ones) and upon that to diſcoutſe, or at the bottom or margin thereof to ſet downe the hiſtorie thereof.</p>
            <p>This one map, is the generall theſis, or doctrine I ſhall draw out of all the parts of the text, or wherein I ſhall draw together all the parts of the text, thus:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> What ever the world vainely promiſe themſelves,   yet the godly in all ages hope for new <hi>Heavens</hi> and a <hi>new Earth,</hi> of a righteous reformed Church, according to Gods promiſe.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:157041:8"/>
            <p>As for our hiſtorie or diſcourſe to be added or annexed to this doctrinall map, it conſiſts of the explication, vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, probation, demonſtration, and application of if.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Explication</hi> (for the illation of the Doctrine from the text is moſt plaine, I neede not inſiſt upon it.) The knot is, how the godly in all ages expected a reformed Church,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> which we explaine thus: That as upon the <hi>Firſt fall,</hi> God made the firſt and grand promiſe of raiſing the Church; ſo ever and anon as the Church tooke ſome wrenches of her old hurt, ſo the Lord renewed, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged the firſt grand promiſe. When the Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a ſecond blow, in the murther, of <hi>Abel,</hi> the Lord bound her up, with the birth of <hi>Seth,</hi> and a propheſie upon him.<note place="margin">Gen. 4.25.</note> 
               <hi>And Adam knew his wife againe, and ſhe bare a ſonne, and called his name Seth. For God</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>hath appointed me another ſeede in ſtead of Abel, whom Caine ſlew.</hi> When the Church in <hi>Seths</hi> poſteritie grew ſore ſicke, then the Lord cheered the Church in <hi>Noah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 6.2. Gen. 5.29. Gen. 6.18.</note> 
               <hi>Hee ſhall comfort her, with thee ſaith the Lord will I eſtabliſh my Covenant.</hi> When by the drowning of the world, the Church was almoſt fallen into her grave, then the Lord raiſed her to life by a gratious promiſe to that moſt eminent Son (<hi>i.e. Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 9.26.27.</note> King of <hi>Salem,</hi> and of righteouſneſſe.) When the Church fell from the buildings of the tower of <hi>Babel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 11.</note> that ſhe was confounded in her language, like one ſpeechleſſe, or amazed with a fall, then God renewed the grand char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the firſt promiſe with inlargements to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his poſteritie.<note place="margin">Gen. 12.</note> And at the ſame time that it was prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied and after performed, that the Church ſhould ſinke as low as the clay pits, and brick kilnes of Egypt, was it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and after proportionably performed, that ſhee ſhould be advanced by Gods power in <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 15. Exod. 12. 1 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. Sam. 3.19. 20.21. 1 Sam. 8. 1 Sam. 13.14.</note> When the Church was lapſed, by <hi>Elies</hi> ſonnes, <hi>Samuel</hi> is choſen, and manifeſted by ſpeciall ſignes that that the Lord had appointed him as a ſupport to the Church. When things declined by <hi>Samuels</hi> ſonnes, and the ill propping it up by <hi>Saul,</hi> then <hi>David</hi> was promiſed, as a ſure and perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:157041:8"/>ſtay, in himſelfe and his poſteritie. Finally, when the Church had that great blow in <hi>Babylon,</hi> whereof ſhee lay ſicke ſeventy yeares, then was Chriſt promiſed,<note place="margin">Dan. 9. All the chapter.</note> the <hi>mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus inſtaurator.</hi> The ſtay of all ſtayes for ever. So that when Chriſt came, and began the new Teſtament, was <hi>Mirabilis annus,</hi> the admired period of the Church. All thoſe periods of reſtoring and comforting the Ghurch in the Old Teſtament were but <hi>praeludia</hi> prefaces to this one of Chriſt comming in the New Teſtament. But this great reſtitution of the Church of the New Teſtament hath ſeverall particular periods before it come to that <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaurationem maximam;</hi> O that greateſt and inaugmentable reſtitution at the end of the world. For that is called (and well may) a <hi>reſtitution. Whom the heavens muſt containe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the time of reſtitution of all things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 3.21.</note> For Saint <hi>Peter</hi> had ſeene one great period of the New Teſtament reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, from his fiſhing to his fiſhing after men (as Chriſt promiſed and propheſied) yet he thinks not that the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going promiſes of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> were yet quite emptied. Some payments yet due, ſome of the fart, and ſtrokings of theſe <hi>breſts of conſolation</hi> yet to be milked out.<note place="margin">Iſaiah 66.11. Some thinke Saint Iohn lived till neere an 100. yeares after Chriſt.</note> 
               <hi>Nevertheleſſe we looke for new heavens, &amp;c.</hi> And Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the longeſt living Apoſtle after Chriſt, had ſeene more of the effect of Chriſts reſtoring the Church; yet doth hee propheſie in the <hi>Revelation</hi> of ſeven particular periods of the Church of the New Teſtament to come; in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſeales, the ſeven trumpets, ſeven thunders, and ſeven viols. All which in briefe, for our underſtanding them in ſhort, may be reduced to theſe two heads.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, That from Chriſts time, till our time was the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall   reformation, particular, and interrupted.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, that after this time or not long hence (as we ſhall ſhew more after, in the uſe of examination:) That   Apoſtolicall condition of the Churches reformation, that hath beene but in few places or Kingdoms here and there,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat. 24.14.</hi> The Goſpel ſhall bee preached to all the world.</note> and with many interruptions, tranſplantations and the like, ſhall from thence forward be univerſall (as wide over the face of the earth, as God will ever have it) and as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:157041:9"/>and uninterrupted, as is ſutable for a Church not yet in heaven it ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>indication.</hi> Becauſe a doubt riſeth out of this expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, we inſert this next, before probation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Object.</hi>   The objection is, that if there be ſo many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and periods of the Churches reformation, how ſhall each age know how much belongs to their time.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi>   The anſwer is, that firſt, to each age to which belongs a perticular promiſe, God gives a ſpeciall light, to compare the promiſe and the event together. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by conſideration of evens yet unfulfilled in former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; Antichriſt not yet pulled downe. The Goſpel not yet preached to all the world.<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.20.</note> The Jewes not yet conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. That the Churches teachers ſhould be no more dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into a corner.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> hath meaſured out the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Church by periods, of halfeings; <hi>Daniels</hi> great period for his time to Chriſt (which was about 490. yeares) diſtinguiſhing them into about 250 yeares. So the Church (that caſteth up far greater peeces of chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie) may the more eaſie account how the Church paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth through any of her ſeven two hundred and fifties, eſpecially of the firſt ſixe; ſo plainely noted by Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> by ſeverall events and circumſtances. For as Eclipſes of the Sunne or Moone, or ſuch remarkable events, are the <hi>Time-markes</hi> of cronologie, that in computation of hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of yeares, not one yeare is loſt. So the ſevens of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents ſet downe by Saint <hi>John,</hi> are the ſtages of the courſe of times moſt eaſily pointed at.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Probation,</hi> wee goe no further for proofe then Saint <hi>Iohn, Coeve,</hi> and of the ſame time with Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> who alſo was told by the ſpirit of God, that though the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> touching the new created heavens were to be fulfilled in this life, that yet the events were yet to come. And therefore that the Church might know them more diſtinctly, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſets them downe more largely, ſo as in every verſe throughout that 21. chapter of the <hi>Revelation</hi> (wherein hee handles the point)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:157041:9"/>there is a plaine argument, that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> cannot bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of heaven above (as ſome would) but of the new heauen here below.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Demonstration,</hi> the reaſon why the Church hopes, is in regard of God. The reaſon why the Lord gave the Church that ground of hope, is in regard of the Church.</p>
            <p>The Church hopes, in regard of God. <hi>i.e.</hi> in regard of his promiſe to the Church. There would be no looking, no ſight, if there were no colour and light, no ground of word, and a Prophet or an Apoſtle from heaven to give light of it.</p>
            <p>And the Lord makes thoſe promiſes by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and gives us more light of them by his Apoſtles, in regard of his compaſſion to the Church.</p>
            <p>To remove her evills.</p>
            <p>To promote her good.</p>
            <p>To remove the evils of the Church, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Nothingneſſe.</item>
                  <item>Childiſhneſſe.</item>
                  <item>Ruſtineſſe.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>That the Church might not decline either towards no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or childiſhneſſe and fooliſhneſſe, or ruſtineſſe, and ſinfulnes. For what is originall to the Church, the Church is inclined to be actuall in, if ſhe be in her declenſion, not in her ſpirituall augmentation.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Adams</hi> fall was the grand wound given the Church, to make her decline, to breake her, and imprayre her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, yea and at firſt almoſt brought her to nothing. So then God made the Church the firſt grand promiſe to put her in hope, that as long as the world ſtood ſhee ſhould not turne into nothing, ſhe ſhould not bee annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated.</p>
            <p>After this, all the times of the old Teſtament, eſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of the Fathers, the Church grew ſo childiſh, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but rudiments, the rattles of the ceremoniall law, the guilded corners of things, ſhaddowed landskips of things, would give her content. Of theſe the Apoſtle ſpeakes in his Epiſtle to <hi>Galat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chapters 2.3.4.</note> Therefore leaſt the Church
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:157041:10"/>ſhould reſt in theſe, the Lord by his Prophts in the old Teſtament, propheſied and promiſed a more excellent eſtate under the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>Finally, when this time was paſt, that the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was begun, the Church no ſooner obtained ſome reſt from perſecution, but ſhee grew ruſty with ambition, contention, and other aberrations, both of opinion, and practiſe.<note place="margin">See <hi>Fox</hi> Acts and Mon. in <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
               </note> As is apparent ſoone after <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great his time: and neerer both of times and places, how reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe cauſeth the Churches ruſtineſſe. Therefore that ſtill the Church might hold up her head and looke beyond all theſe things, to a more glorious condition then the world could afford; the Lord by the Apoſtles ſét before them the promiſes of the new heaven and earth.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. By Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> in text.</item>
               <item>2. By Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> inlarging and inculeating them, in <hi>Revel.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Becauſe <hi>vice versâ,</hi> by a retrograde motion, from ruſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Church will decline to childiſhneſſe. Ruſt wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens the mettle, ſinne weakens the ſoule. And ruſty old age makes a man twy-child. And from childiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will the Church decline towards nothingneſſe. In <hi>Rome,</hi> if not nearer this may be ſeene. From abundance of ſinfulneſſe, through eaſe and idleneſſe the Church grew to abundance of ceremoniouſneſſe. From thence, ſhe fell into idolatrouſneſſe, and ſo farre ſhe went there, ſhee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came utterly nothing.</p>
            <p>To prevent therefore ſuch a gradation, and diſſolution of the Church; both in regard of his owne <hi>Compaſsion,</hi> and in regard of that <hi>impreſſion</hi> hee hath made upon the Church, hee hath promiſed to lend her his aſſiſtance to raiſe her to this glorious condition.</p>
            <p>In regard of his <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> for if when the Church wanted no goodneſſe, he promiſed her greatneſſe in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>liſe, much more now in more diſtreſſe, that ſhee hath i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oulke a greatneſſe, but wants goodneſſe, will hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe it, and performe.</p>
            <p>In regard of that <hi>impreſſion</hi> the Lord hath made upon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:157041:10"/>the Church, for if God hath ſtampt on nature a generall abhorring of <hi>vacuum,</hi> of a voyde place, emptie of any na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall body (for that would breake off ſome linckes of the chaine and faſt dependance of the naturall univerſe, and cauſe a ſelfe annihilation of nature more or leſſe;) And therefore nature hath deviſed many <hi>changes,</hi> (generation, corruption, alteration, augmentation, diminution, locall motion, and that of particular bodies, contrary to their owne proper natures; as water to aſcend in a pumpe, Aire to deſcend into the earth, in an earthquake) to ſhift her naturall ſonnes out of the way upon attempts of <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuum</hi> that none of them may periſh: how much more is there an impreſſion of grace on the Church, of abhorring this leaſt ſelfe annihilation, or looſing any of its ſpirituall perfection; and is moſt loth to be worſe, but deſires to be as much better as ſhee may. Therefore, as the Lord helpeth the naturall world to conſerve it ſelfe, ſo hee hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the Church by efficacious promiſes, to ſuſtaine her ſpirituall condition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To promote the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches good, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>To draw on the Church.</item>
                  <item>To draw up the Church.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>To draw on the Church, in patience and holineſſe. So runnes the context with the ſucceeding verſe; <hi>Wherefore (beloved) ſeeing that ye looke for ſuch things,</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> promiſed new heavens &amp; earth, as it is in the text) <hi>be diligent that ye may be found of him in Chriſt, without ſpot and blameles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. i. 2.</note> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with this that of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing we are compaſſed about with ſo great a cloud of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, let us lay aſide every weight, and the ſinne which doth ſo eaſily beſet us, and let us runne with patience the race that is ſet before us, looking to Ieſus, the authour and finiſher of our faith.</hi> As aparent promiſing his married children to bee a daily friend to them, to build their decayed houſe new for them, and to make every thing new is a great incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to them more patiently to beare the deprivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their parents perſonall preſence and the combrance of the many cares and <hi>troubles in the fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.28.</note> (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſpeakes) attending on marriage; ſo Chriſt perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:157041:11"/>being gone into heaven, till the full reſtitution of all things, promiſing his children to build them a new world,<note place="margin">Revel. 21.</note> or a new citie, <hi>i.e.</hi> many houſes, and to make all ſpirituall things new for them; it doth much ſtay their hearts: It makes them hold up their heads <hi>as after a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption drawing nigh; as after a recovery to life, after a lying at the point of death.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11.15.</note> As a travellour, the more hee ſees the approach of his journeyes end, the more hee is cheared; ſo ſpiritually in this.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To draw up the Church, to make her as more heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, ſo more heavenly. And that in her judgement, as well as her deſires. For if an eſtate of the reformed Church on earth, be called heaven, &amp; compared to a new heaven, how excellent is heaven it ſelfe, which is the patterne &amp; exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plarie cauſe it ſelfe which this lower heaven doth but imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate?<note place="margin">Acts 3.2.</note> If the gates of the materiall temple were beautifull, how beautiful is that temple of heaven, where God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is immediately in fulneſſe of glory, <hi>whoſe maker &amp; buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is God?</hi> If one part of this new heaven be ſo glorious, viz.<note place="margin">Heb. 3.4. 2 Cor. 3.5.6.</note> the Miniſtrie of the Goſpel, in ſo much that the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie of the law, in the Moſaicall Church, had no glory in compariſon, how tranſcendent is the glory of the whole ſtate of glory?<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2, 8.9.10.</note> If eye had not ſeene, nor eare heard, nor heart conceived the excellency of the Goſpel, till God revealed it experimentally by his ſpirit; much leſſe can it be apprehended what are the heavens of glory, till we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the glory in heaven. And as theſe propheſies and promiſes doe make the Church more heavenly in her ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, ſo in her affections. As woings make lovers minds betrothings, betrothings make them minde mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying; ſo theſe woing and betrothing reſtitutions doe cauſe the Church to long for that condition, when the Church ſhall be as a <hi>bride ready trimmed</hi> to be fully married and enter into heaven to ſup with the lambe,<note place="margin">Revel. 21.</note> Chriſt Jeſus her husband in glory. As the more ſucceſſe the ſayler hath in his voyage rounde the world, the more acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance he hath with, and delight in the new hemiſpheres, of the heavens, and new conſtellations of ſtarres; ſo the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:157041:11"/>further the Church on earth goes with her <hi>full-ſaite</hi> of <hi>knowledge, faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> coll. 2.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Heb. 10.22. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Heb. 6.11.</note> and <hi>hope</hi> of the new militant Church on earth, the more ſhee will diſcerne and deſire the laſt and beſt heaven of heavens.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine being thus inferred, explained, vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, proved &amp; demonſtrated, is uſefull for
<list>
                  <item>Inſtruction.</item>
                  <item>Examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  <item>Humiliation</item>
                  <item>Conſolation</item>
                  <item>Exhortation</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, for Inſtruction, or information of the judgement, in three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the thoughts and hopes of the world are very much at rovers, and randume, beſides and aſquint from the common cauſe; the Common good. So the Doctrine (cloſely grounded on the text) <hi>whatever the world promiſe themſelves, &amp;c.</hi> whatever they tinck, or thinke, they think not as the godly, hope not as the godly, intent on the common good: yea who can gueſſe what their vaine thoughts or hopes are? <hi>The common good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>or evill of the Church is nothing to them, ſo they paſſe by. Lam.</hi> 1.12. If they bee preſented with conſiderations of Divine juſtice, future judgement, in caſe of non-repentance; at theſe either they mocke, or are as ſtupified, through wilfull ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance. So our Apoſtle in the beginning of this chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before the text. They returne to their former walke in their own vomit, or common mire, or ſalt matſhes of the world, <hi>ut juvat immenſo ſpatiantem vivere Caelo,</hi> like vaine-headed men in a walke, whiles they ſee moſt of heaven, they thinke leaſt of heaven. If their ſpirits be a wakened, they turne their edge the cleane contrary way. If a Rome (as one once ſaid in an Apothegme) be to be ſould, theſe worldlings theſe <hi>terrae fily,</hi> theſe roving archers are the men that ſet the price on her. A <hi>Machiavellian</hi> a tribe of friends, a kingdome of common good, for his own ends. For he holds cloſe to his <hi>theoreme,</hi> or rule. <hi>Pereant amici, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do intercidant inimici.</hi> He is at the ſame paſſe to put off at a low price, ſome few great ones, as many inferiour ones.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:157041:12"/>Now he can as trimly act the Judas. If the K. of the Jewes may be bought and ſold, for <hi>Quid aabis</hi> at a rate, he will betray him. Theſe are the Popes Merchants and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets,<note place="margin">Revel. 18.13.</note> and his butchers ſhambles, to deale <hi>in ſlaves and ſoules of men.</hi> But one the other ſide let theſe worldlings meet in the face any opportunitie of advancing the common good, to bind up the wounded <hi>Levites,</hi> to preſerve many a poore Soſthenes from beating,<note place="margin">Acts</note> 
               <hi>like Gallio, they</hi> care for none of thoſe things, eſpecially if the buſineſſe of ſo great conſequence as to rebuild the decayed temple, they ſtick heavily &amp; anſwer lazily,<note place="margin">Hag. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>The time is not yet come to ſet about it.</hi> If a church a Kingdom ſhould put themſelves into ſuch mens hands, intruſt themſelves with ſuch moles how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly and remedileſſely might all bee betrayed. And therfore it is not a ſmall mercy, that the Lord hath found out ſo many worthies of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to be faithfull to <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Thing wherein this Doctrine doth <hi>inſtruct</hi> is this, It is the common condition of godly men, that though they dwell in the heavens of the Church on earth, as long as they dwell in the old heavens, in that ſtate of the Church that is old in compariſon of the new to come, they ſhall bee where there is a want of righteouſneſſe. There will be ſtore if not of corporall, bee ſure <hi>of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all wickedneſſes in</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">So Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>heavenly places.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.2.</note> This heaven is ſeamed and fringed about with Hell. Things are not right there is a want of righteouſneſſe in the<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 12.1. <hi>Hebrew</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>vilitas.</hi> Gen. 15. Zech. 1. Pſal. 137.</note> abſtract So when the godly dwell in Egypt, in Babylon, ſtill they found righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe to bee a Phaenix a ſcare bird. Alwaies thus it will be (be we contented with old things as long as wee will; I meane ſtill the old Heavens:) either, there will bee a defect of righteoſneſſe; Or, a defection from righteouſneſſe; Or a diſaffection againſt righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>A defect of righteouſneſſe, either men will bee igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or negligent of righteouſneſſe. Ignorant, when men looke not after the righteouſneſſe of God (the originall of all righteouſeſſe) <hi>but goe about to eſtabliſh their owne rightouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.3.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo doe not ſubmit to the righteouſneſſe of God.</hi> Thus it is with men, when they are blind at the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:157041:12"/>Doctrine, or fumble at the practiſe of righteouſneſſse. So ſtubborne Papiſts, and ignorant ſottiſh Proteſtants; they ſeeke a righteouſneſſe in blankes: as that they meane no hurt. In negative <hi>'Phariſeiſme, they are not this nor that:</hi> In things of no life, or activitie in themſelves, <hi>viz.</hi> in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, <hi>as their, wee have faſted.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 58.3. Luke 18.12.</note> And that <hi>often too</hi> (though too oft to bee good) However; Performances of duties, are good praiſes not payments to God thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings to God: No ſalvation given to men. For they all are nothing in themſelves, though done never ſo well,<note place="margin">Iohn 5.39.40. Obſerve well and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the word <hi>ſearch</hi> is to bee read indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, rather then impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively as a command. Compare the 39 and 40 ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes together it well eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. Zech. 13.1. Gen. 4. Heb. 11.</note> but as they finde and center upon Chriſt: And it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with the moſt of men to build their falſe righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe where the neſt may eaſily bee pulled downe. Vpon ſome non cauſes, ſome meere probables, or ſome peeces or fragments of obedience, ſome care of the ſecond Table with neglect of the firſt, or contrariwiſe: To ſeeke righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, or put righteouſneſſe in any of all theſe, is as vaine as to ſeeke waters in the Mill-ſtreame, when they are exactly pind up in the Mill-pond. <hi>If the fountain of Chriſts righteouſneſſe be not opened</hi> upon the <hi>uncleanneſſe of men,</hi> how ſhall they be waſhed righteous in perſon &amp; nature. And if not righteous in perſon &amp; nature, how ſhall they practiſe any righteouſnes towards men, as a righteouſneſſe? much leſſe can they doe any performances of religion ſo rightly as to make of them any ſmall peece of righteouſnes. <hi>Abell by faith. i. e.</hi> in Chriſt, <hi>offered an acceptable ſacrifice.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Chriſt is made to us righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. two laſt.</note> before wee can make or doe any thing, ſo as we may <hi>glory in God,</hi> or take comfort in him, and not in our ſelves. 2. Negligent of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, when men know of the fountaine Chriſt; of the Scriptures, the promiſes, the cocke to let goe that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of faith, the only hand to turne it; yet are of a ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh nature and practiſe: ſtrive not to be eminent in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, eminent in the aſſurance and application of Chriſts righteouſneſſe, and in the inſurance and warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that application by the evidence of a converſation of righteouſneſſe as a Chriſtian. I ſay this ſort at moſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 10, 22.23. Epheſ. 5.15.</note> ſtrive not to be eminent; <hi>to beleeue confidently;</hi> to wake <hi>accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly;</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:157041:13"/>lye along as contented to live as bed-ridden Chrſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, from hand to mouth. No good ſuit to their backs, of Chriſts righteouſneſſe, by application. No good glaſſe upon that ſuite, or profeſſion of Chriſt of more holy and innocent converſation. No good warmth by putting on of Chriſt, as by the ſpirits infuſion of abundance of grace. This Spittle or Hoſpitall of pittifull Chriſtians; theſe impotent profeſſors (grant they be true) improve not their ſtock. And ſo at every turne of great expence of much faith, and hope, and prayer, in a ſickly time of feares and afflictions, they are found to bee exceeding poore.</p>
            <p>A defection or declining from righteouſneſſe more and more appeares oft in this old Heaven. As when peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Miniſters, the ſtarres, and the ſtarers after them erre from the right doctrine, and doctrine of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; when they diſlike the puritie, power, and plenty of it: what neede (thinke they) ſuch grinding the edge of the ſword of the ſpirit the word ſo thinne? what neede ſuch nice and cloſe dividings by it?<note place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> And leſſe of any preaching will ſerve (once a day enough of conſcience, <hi>i. e.</hi> of their conſcience and enemy to the rule of conſcience,) leſſe profeſſion is enough,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.1.</note> unleſſe men will be too forward. They like a mixture that may abate the acrimonie of ſound truth, as not induring truth in the ſimple. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ingredients theſe men give and take, in the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are ſmokey diſtinctions, popiſh evaſions, carnall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, phariſaicall colluſions, human rules and traditions, fleſhly formes of worſhip, ſeeming pretences of flattering devotions, by all which to blinde the eyes and puddle the ſtreames of the Scriptures <hi>(&amp; ſibires, non ſe rebus ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere.)</hi> For they make the Scrptures by violence to juſtifie theſe, not to try theſe, juſt by the Scriptures. This pack or heard of men, are like horſes that firſt pounce, or plunge with their feet, and mudde the water, and then drinke. They put in their corrupt ingredients to the word, or doctrine, and then give it, and take it to drinke.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the want of righteouſneſſe in the old heaven
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:157041:13"/>appeares by a frequent diſaffection to righteouſneſſe, to deale, and to unrighteouſly doe ſet againſt, and abuſe righteouſneſſe, to bee unrighteous both againſt God and man.</p>
            <p>Firſt, againſt God; Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt. The world will ſmite <hi>God,</hi> by oathes, curſings, impreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, blaſphemies: God never wronged them; he that is wronged by them, was the maker of them.<note place="margin">Acts 17.28.</note> 
               <hi>Jn him they live and move, &amp;c.</hi> againſt whom they move and live ſo wickedly; they debaſe and vilifie God to his face. They preferre every creature, yea every ſinne they have a minde to commit, above God himſelfe. To commit ſpirituall adultry, idolaterie, in preferring the firſt, and witchcraft to love, and put confidence in the devill in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the ſecond, is nothing with them.<note place="margin">Pſal. 11 9.</note> 
               <hi>God is good, and doth good</hi> to them. And they are evill and doe evill againſt him, as a meet requital. As for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> if they do not ſweare by his precious wounds, paſſion, body, death, ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall bread, they will be ſure to ſlight his merits,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings as things of no neceſſitie or uſe to them. His Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel to them a pack of fables, no more faith and credit (to ſpeake of effectuall faith) doe they give to it. As once a Biſhop one of the Popes ſaid: how great a gaine have we "made of this fable of the Goſpell? They live as if they ſhould never dye, and die as if after that they ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver live. As another of the Roman Biſhops a Pope was unreſolved at his laſt dying pillow. Saying, <q>now I ſhall (ſaith he) be reſolved of three things.
<list>
                     <item>1 Whether there be a God?</item>
                     <item>2. Whether the ſoule bee immortall?</item>
                     <item>3. Whether there bee an Heaven and Hell?</item>
                  </list>
               </q>
And for the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> they will jeare and ſcoffe at that holineſſe that is wrought in mens ſpirits, by that holy ſpirit: yea hating, and oppoſing all holy profeſſion and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they are unrighteous againſt men, both themſelves and others. They will put out both their own eyes to put out one of their godly neighbours: like the Philiſtins that ſtopped <hi>Iſaacks</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">A fountaine and an eye in Hebrew, called by the ſame name <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> wells, to their owne hurt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:157041:14"/>as well as his. They reproach religion as faſt as they can wherein they doe as the Roman that cut off the bridge he ſtood on, although hee muſt needs fall into the river himſelfe, ſo as hee might drowne his enemies. Religion and profeſſion, is the bridge to carry them over the lake of hell to heaven, yet its no matter, they will cut it off by ſharpe ſarcaſmes and deriſions, that by their good will there ſhould bee no ſuch conſcience-troubling profeſſion upon earth Therefore they let flee freely at others, that ſeeme to have any thing of God in them. Theſe world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, theſe <hi>earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>th,</hi> (as the Prophet ſpeakes) all dirt, will bedaub the Saints moſt odiouſly. They will <hi>ſmite them,</hi> as <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>miah with the tongue.</hi> Name-blaſt them. They will ſmite them in the body,<note place="margin">Acts</note> as Saint <hi>Paul on the mouth,</hi> yea <hi>on the back<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Yea they will ſtick yet cloſer to them. They will ſmite them in the conſcience, ſtick a dagger of offence in it pull it out who can. So in the ten perſecutions, by feares to make men ſacrifice to the idoll. So in the Phillip and Marian perſecutions, to threaten men till they made them abjure and forſweare the truth. And when they have wounded thus, will they, can they heale?<note place="margin">Howbeit God would not looſe his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, but his ſpirit made them keepe their firſt vow in Baptiſme, and ſo after they ſuffered death for Chriſt volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily. Exech 13.22.</note> no. If the Phariſees draw a Judas into a fact of Treaſon againſt Chriſt, all they anſwer to him comming to them with his conſience dreadfully bleeding, <hi>ſee you to it, what is that to us?</hi> much leſſe doe they regard the <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of a Ioſeph,</hi> although (as in that <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.) cauſed by them. It is their joy <hi>to make the hearts of Gods people ſad, whom the Lord would not have to be ſad, and to ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked.</hi> Marke <hi>the hands,</hi> for ſinne cannot ſtrengthen the heart. And yet they thinke they come not cloſe enough, and therefore they will give the Saints one deepe ſtab more. They will ſmite them in the very image of God in them. You be the <hi>holy brethren.</hi> And how are they brethren but by being children of one Father, God; &amp; having his <hi>divine nature</hi> in them?<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4.</note> And how are they holy, but by &amp; from God wiſhing &amp; working them to be <hi>holy, as he is holy?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. Mat. 3.7.</note> yet this holineſſe they venemouſly (juſt as a generation of ſharp toothed vipers) bite at. You be the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:157041:14"/>ones, pure ones, the Puritants. Which laſt terme hath beene a long liv'd murtherer to kill ſound doctrine, holy life, ſobrietie, equitie, all that is good. As ſaid a Parliament man in Parliament, <q>the word Puritan in the mouth of an Arminian, ſignifies an Orthodoxe divine; in the mouth of a drunkard ſignifies a ſober man; and in the mouth of a Papiſt ſignifies a Proteſtant.</q> So generall is that name grown now, that with it the wicked Iſmae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites open their mouths <hi>wide, make</hi> an odious <hi>wide mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 57.4.</note> 
               <hi>and ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt themſelves.</hi> So that their mouthes being veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and their throats hiſſing, this name in them is as a ſting to make them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ike the dragon, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.4. ready and prepared to devoure a young profeſſor before hee is hatch't. Therefore pious Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſeeing the miſchiefe comming upon religion, by ſuch approbious termes, made an injunction againſt them, that they might not thunder ſtrike, or lightning blaſt or cerebrate the gay bloſſomes of tender profeſſion. And I live in hope to ſee a good law enacted againſt ſo bad a malefactor, as this ſoule-killing Nick-name hath beene for theſe many yeares, even farre too many. And thus, and thus, and thus will the wicked ſmight and ſmite the godly, the meane while,<note place="margin">Revel. chap. 13 10. chap. 14.12.</note> if the Saints lie ſtill (and if they doe <hi>here is the patience of the Saints,</hi>) the wicked ſmight on, and ſtrike, as if they cudgelled onely a ſack, not a Saint. The ſmighters ſing whiles the Saints cry. The ſmighters curſe whiles the Saints pray. The ſmighters ſhed the Saints blood, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es they ſhed teares. If on the otherſide the Saints ever ſo modeſtly ſtirre in the behalfe of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, what a ſtirre doe thoſe men preſently make. If the god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ſpeake <hi>of,</hi> and in the behalfe of righteouſneſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, then they jeare them. Theſe be factious, all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or law; they be preciſe phariſaicall, hypocriticall, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to be after Goſpel. If the Godly ſpeake to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe men <hi>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> righteouſneſſe, and juſtice, then they will uſe them, as the So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mites did <hi>Lot</hi> (at leaſt ſay they would) viz. worſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 19 9.</note> for ſpeaking but reaſon. They will miſuſe them woſe for intreating them to be better;<note place="margin">Exod. 2.17, &amp;c.</note> as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t with the Iſraelites.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:157041:15"/>
            <p>If the Godly ſpeake to God much in prayer to procure, or adminiſter to them juſtice, and righteouſneſſe; then their ſmall friends, thoſe ſons of the world will call them <hi>Lollards,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox.</hi> Act. Mon. in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> time.</note> becauſe they cry Lord, Lord unto their God. If they bee hunted with perſecution, ſo that they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to turne night into day, to pray before day or a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of righteous uſage among men, and to worſhip the maker of night and day, then thoſe ſonnes of Belial ſpirt that poyſon upon them, that they riſe early, to worſhip the Sunne-riſing.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox</hi> Act. Mon. of the ten per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions.</note> If they profeſſe their beliefe of, and in all the Scriptures, that promiſe them ſuccour and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound to them examples how the Lord hath delivered his people from their enemies, as <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and by him the Iſraelites from the Philiſtines, by the jaw-bone of an Aſſe, then they caſt upon the Chriſtians this Heil-hatch't obloquie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox</hi> ibid.</note> and <hi>made-ly</hi> that the Chriſtians worſhipped an Aſſes head. If the Saints profeſſe they love the righteous, and eſpecially that right doctrine and righteous conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation they confeſſed and profeſſed as <hi>Waldus, Hus, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Calvin, &amp;c.</hi> then they call them in ſcorne, <hi>Walden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Huſſites,</hi> &amp;c. As if either of theſe was the higheſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall of that truth they profeſſe; and that they <hi>were</hi> as very Hereticks, as they <hi>would</hi> have thoſe to be, in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of them and their adherents. Finally, if theſe poore harmeleſſe ſheepe are worried, and wearied from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> 
               <hi>to mountaines, and dens, and Caves,</hi> and ſo part with all, and kiſſe povertie with pietie, rather then in riches to looſe Chriſt, yet the wicked leave them not, but as the dragon, caſt out theſe floods, vomit out this filthy flegme after them, that they are <hi>poore men of Lyons,</hi> the religion doth nought, but make men fooles, and turne beggers (as many amongſt us now adayes can ſay, on leſſe occaſion) and that ſuch flying Chriſtians are<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> wolves of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocks. <hi>Fox</hi> Act. mon.</note> 
               <hi>Turri-lupins.</hi> If theſe are not touches enough to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the unrighteouſneſſe of the old heavens, then mens cyes are old, and their judgements u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>righteous, that they cannot or will not ſee the right. For proportionably ſtill it is ſo, every particular way of piety and equity, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:157041:15"/>ſtanding for theſe, get an ill report, and a ſcornefull name, from the black mouthes of the ſonnes of darkeneſſe. As that they are Factioniſts, Humoriſts, Scrupulous fooles, Proteſtants ſtript of their witts, enemies to the common peace, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This Doctrine <hi>inſtructeth</hi> us in this. That as long as the Church dwelleth under, or in the old heavens, though ſhee may in her true members have ſome new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and righteouſneſſe in themſelves, yet in regard of the preſent <hi>oppoſition</hi> of this old unrighteous world, and the <hi>indiſpoſition</hi> of the preſent old Church, contented with her old wrinckled, ragged condition, as if ſhee knew no better; that newneſſe and righteouſneſſe are nothing to that ſhe ſhall have, when ſhe ſhall ſee and ſue for a better condition. The footing of this inſtruction upon the doctrine is this; that the Church hopes for that ſhee yet hath not. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſo long ſince Chriſt, and the Church ſtill ſo long ſince Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> ſees more in the promiſe,<note place="margin">Hope that is ſeene is no hope, Rom. 8.</note> all is not yet ſhaken into the lappe of the Church. She hath in the Apoſtles time, and in all times of true conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſome <hi>newneſſe, Epheſ.</hi> 4.23. <hi>Colloſ.</hi> 3.10. <hi>i. e.</hi> ſome perſonall new qualities, ſome particular new diſpoſitions and actions. Againe, ſhe hath ſome <hi>righteouſneſſe.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.31. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11.12. <hi>i. e.</hi> Relatively righteous in Chriſt, applied by faith, and imputed by God; perſonally in her particular members righteous, with qualities and actions. But theſe are nothing to that ſhee ſhall have.<note place="margin">Bee <hi>yee.</hi> Ephe. 4.23. Heaven and Earth. Renewed, Eph. 4.23. Col. 3.10</note> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> putts a difference: how a <hi>few members</hi> ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, then all the <hi>body</hi> of the Church joyntly, through the whole <hi>Habitable</hi> of the Church; now in qualities and actions, then as it were in the very <hi>ſubſtance;</hi> Now in the <hi>Concret;</hi> But then in the <hi>abſtract,</hi> ſhall the Church be <hi>new,</hi> and <hi>righteous. All</hi> the word of the Church ſo.<note place="margin">New.</note> 
               <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. Greated as a <hi>new ſubſtance. Iſa.</hi> 65.17. made <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> in the abſtract. <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.8.<note place="margin">Righteouſly. Tit. 2.12.</note> All her newneſſe now is but as the new-moone to a ſevenfold ſun-ſhine. All her righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is but as a glaring Diamond ring on one finger,<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.26.</note> to a whole ſuit of cloth of gold of ſun-beames, nay of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:157041:16"/>ſunne, nay of the ſunne of righteouſneſſe. <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1. And in this glory and ſtate ſhall righteouſneſſe dwell as Maſter of the houſe of the Church, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in every roome and corner. But as yet, hitherto the Church hath beene withheld from this eminent condition <hi>partly</hi> by the oppoſition of the old world; mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the old things of ceremonious Iudaiſme,<note place="margin">Mat. 9.16.</note> and Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſme (which ſpoyle the newneſſe of the Church.) Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, and withholding righteouſneſſe.<note place="margin">Rom. 1. verſe verſe 18.32.</note> And <hi>partly</hi> by the indiſpoſition of the old infirmitie of the Church, to be darke ſighted and ſtiffe in her limbs, ſpiritually to ſee, and move for that of her dowry behind. Shee hath beene examinated, unſouled and exoculated. So that as Chriſt ſaid to the Diſciples,<note place="margin">Iohn 16.12.</note> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the Hebrewes, ſhe was unfit to heare of and ſee a better condition.<note place="margin">Heb. 5.11.12.</note> She hath beene beaten with unrighteouſneſſe, and bound from righteouſneſſe, that ſhe could not preach, ſpeake, diſpute or practiſe righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 125. Pſal. 37.6. Mat. 13.43.12.20.</note> till ſhee was black and blew with her bonds and blowes, and looked old with ſorrow, yet hath beene flattered to bee the moſt knowing and righteous Church. But theſe to come when new.</p>
            <p>Vſe of examination.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Who are the true godly.</item>
               <item>2. What the new heavens, &amp;c. promiſed by God.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, EXAMINATION, who godly In gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, they are perſons of an excellent hope of an hearty heavenly heroick hope. They looke and expect for what ever God hath promiſed to them, ſingly to their perſons, or collectively to them in their relation to the Church. <hi>We our ſelves</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>groane within our ſelves, waiting for the adoption,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.23.24.</note> 
               <hi>there demption of our bodies. For wee are ſaved by hope. But hope that is ſeene, is no hope. But if we hope for that we ſee not, then doe we with patience waite for it, or expect it.</hi> As ſure as <hi>Elijah</hi> hoping for raine from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to refreſh him and the whole kingdome, looked for it, ſent his man to view the clouds. So hope mentally lookes for the mercies it hopes for from heaven, for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and the Church. Hope is the eye to faith, as in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:157041:16"/>face is the eye to reaſon, to looke after what we beleeve, or know ſhall come to paſſe. And therefore the Saints from time to time in the Scriptures (marke it you that think ye beleeve) as they profeſſed their faith,<note place="margin">Ezra 10.2. Iob 5.16. Pſal. 42.11. Pſal. 43.5. Pſal. 119.49. Pro. 10.28. Ier. 17.7. Act. 26.6.7.</note> ſo ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they profeſſed their hope. To teach us, no doubt what a barren faith that is, which breedes no hope: what an helpeleſſe faith that will prove, that is an hopeleſſe faith. Let the wicked and ungodly therefore take this as their character to have no true hope. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. For they are the men that are but the imagery, the imaginary of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, that ſeeming to have an eye of hope, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not turne it this way or that way, after that they profeſſe they believe.</p>
            <p>In particular the hope of the true godly man is notable for its
<list>
                  <item>Reſolution</item>
                  <item>Diſtinction</item>
                  <item>Foundation</item>
                  <item>Dimenſion</item>
                  <item>Gradation</item>
               </list>
That is, its
<list>
                  <item>Setledneſſe and courage</item>
                  <item>Difference from falſe</item>
                  <item>Buildings on the promiſe</item>
                  <item>Looking to the Church too</item>
                  <item>Expectance of yet more newneſſe and righteouſneſſe.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>All which ſhew the braveneſſe of the godly mans ſpirit,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> above them that have received onely the ſpirit of the world.</p>
            <p>The reſolution or ſetldneſſe of his hope, ſhewes the godly mans patient ſpirit, patient through courage.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The diſtinction, the betterneſſe of his ſpirit like <hi>Calebs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 14.24. Pſal. 119.80. 2 Tim. 1.7. Phil. 1.20.21. Heb. 11.24.25. Like the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans.</hi> Acts 17.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The foundation ſhewes thee ſoundneſſe of his ſpirit.</p>
            <p>The Dimenſion, or width, ſhewes his publike ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
            <p>And the gradation, his ſublime and heroick ſpirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolution.</hi> The godly mans hope is an hardy hope. For though (as the Doctrine intimates) his hope ſhall bee put to it, and that with ſo much (and more) as breakes or melts away the worlds hope; And although in all ages (eſpecially hitherto) there is ſomewhat ſtill behind even of this promiſe, that is hoped for, and ſo the man is never fully pertaker of his hope: and although the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:157041:17"/>comes apace (that cuts off all hope) and the ſcoffing of the unbelievers haſten it, yet the godly mans hope comes in with a Nevertheleſſe, what ever the world hope; however his hope be put to it, <hi>yet</hi> he will hope. Hope in the <hi>Motion</hi> is an expectation of future happineſſe of this life and that to come,<note place="margin">Spes in motu.</note> grace, and glory, in the inchoation, augmentation, and conſummation. So that in regard of thus much of its nature, hope muſt be, nay is an holding hope.<note place="margin">Spes in vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute.</note> If it be not alwaies of a like bigneſſe and ſtrength; yet it is a long and laſting hope. Hope in the vertue is a boldneſſe of minde, conceived upon Gods promiſed bounty, by which, through the uſe of the meanes, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to all the degrees of happineſſe. So that <hi>is not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med;</hi> it is groundedly confident:<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> though it bee not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratively ſure, like the certainty of reaſon (as it is not ſo contingently certaine as the certainty of bare opinion) yet relatively, in relation to the promiſe, and by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the promiſe, informing for certaine what God will do, it hath an infallible mentall ſpirituall certaintie of <hi>Narration,</hi> nor the man nor his hope can poſſibly bee mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, what hee is told. Nor can hee miſtruſt him that promiſed, whether he will make that good hee told him in the promiſe.<note place="margin">Heb. 6.18, 19.</note> Hope is <hi>an Anchor,</hi> its tooth or beard is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farre off, unſeene; and the ſhip may play about, but not from the Anchor. So the things hoped are not ſeene; The ſoule hovers,<note place="margin">Rom. 8 23.</note> and ſeemes to bee ready to runne into the quick-ſands and ſinke,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. Heb. 6.</note> but that the Anchor hope, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened in the promiſe held toughly. And in this tempeſt the <hi>Anchor</hi> is wrought further into the rocke of Chriſt promiſing, by the windleſſe or engine of prayer. As the Apoſtle ſubjoineth unto hope energeticall and efficatious prayer.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> Thus brave Hope ſhewes her ſelfe fixed, reſolute and valiant both for the man, and the Church. Will the ſpirituall enemies of the particular Chriſtian fight? ſhee will fight, and conquer too. If ſinne and Sathan, and world ſtrike to make him diſpaire,<note place="margin">1 Iohn 5.4. Rom. 5.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> he will by the promiſe get up and ſtampe upon them. Faith ſteps up firſt, hope immediately at the heeles as the Armour-bearer after <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:157041:17"/>and both triumph together: will the backe friends of the Church diſpute; hope will diſpute, and confute too. If difficultie object, hope will anſwer.</p>
            <p>Difficulty objecting, that tampering a reformation, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, it ſpeedily, and throughly, is full of danger to a ſtate, to cauſe Caſmes, and ſuch violences as attend on <hi>vacuum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hope anſwers, that ſhe hopes better things. Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, if reformation, cannot bee dangerous. Papiſts have not beene affraid, in Phillip and Maries dayes to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Religion (the true, to falſe) therefore ſaith hope, ſhee hopes that good proteſtants neede not be affraid to make a reformation, in the out-workes of true religion, eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall offices, and diſcipline, &amp;c. A thing which hath beene done in ſo many places with no miſchievous effect; as in the <hi>Low Countries, Denmarke, Geneva,</hi> yea the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of all Chriſtendom, by Luthers meanes, wherein the ſubſtance of religion was altered, miſchiefed no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, or ſtate matters. Yea <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, his rejecting the Popes ſupremacy, &amp; mining of the Abbeys (a greater matter then the things now talked off) brought no prejudice to Church or ſtate, but a preparative benefit to both. So in <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt time to goe much further. And Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, to returne backe all thoſe turnings of religion, perſons, ceremonies, diſcipline,<note place="margin">Nullus pudor ad meliora tranſire. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ.</note> &amp;c. (invading by Queene <hi>Mary</hi>) did all well ſucceede. So that the Churches neede not repent of any thing they did.</p>
            <p>If Difficulty object, that great is the antiquity of many things in the preſent goverment.</p>
            <p>Hope anſwers, that ſhe hopes whatſoever is ſinne or error may not pleade preſcription. Such things are not <hi>veritatis antiquitas,</hi> but <hi>vetuſtas erroris.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul.</note> Or if but things in nature indifferent, or at firſt of ſome probable uſe, yet as the Brazen Serpent, in the uſe were ſo <hi>altered,</hi> that they were <hi>altared,</hi> though they were ſeene onely in the aire, but made croſſes or ſcratchings of blood in the conſcience, they may ſaith hope (for ought ſhe knowes) very conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:157041:18"/>by good <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> be taken downe: much more muſt ill cuſtomes be cancelled,<note place="margin">Iuſtin.</note> though very <hi>ancient,</hi> if <hi>ill. Conſuetudo non munita ratione non eſt conſuetudo ſed corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tela.</hi> And that in our Church offices, Liturgies, Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and diſcipline are things much to be complained off, we cannot doubt, when the Fathers (though in ſome things parties, at leaſt ſome of them) doe among them make up a great and many voted complaint, againſt all thoſe things we complaine of. The complainers are <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom, Ambroſe, Auſtia, Sedulius, Primaſious, Chryſoſtome, Theodoret, Oecumenius, Theophilact, Cyprian, Ignatius.</hi> And their particular complaints will <hi>Bucer, Gerard, Iewell, Schamier,</hi> and <hi>Voctius</hi> tell you, in heapes and cluſters, if any have not time to reade the fathers themſelves, turne in thoſe named controverters, to any head of Epiſcopacy, diſcipline, &amp;c. and ye may ſtore your ſelves. And no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that theſe Fathers, among the reſt of their invectives, and ſtated queſtions reſolved that Biſhops are not Jure divino; when Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth ſaid to the Spaniſh Embaſſadour, that his Maſter did not know what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, in petitioning that Biſhops ſhould be declared to be <hi>Iure divino</hi> in the Councell of <hi>Trent.</hi> For ſaid the Pope, that being done, they would be as independent as hee the Pope himſelfe.</p>
            <p>If Difficultie object, that if things were ſo amiſſe all this while in the Church, why did not the world heare of them ſooner.</p>
            <p>Hope anſwers, that ſhe hopes the world hath heard of ſomethings from ſome heretofore. And ſhe hopes that men will ſee that later times have ſet a new impreſſion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt upon all Eccleſiaſticall things and perſons, and ſo by ſimpathie, or conſequence upon many ſecular. Men were not permitted to ſpeake, write, diſpute, or any how to meddle with the queſtions now on foot, unleſſe to ſtate them the cleane contrary way. Scholars put upon it that they muſt chifely reade fathers, and Schoolmen. The booke binders found their very trading to be altered. Few books unleſſe written by Papiſts would ſell, among Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:157041:18"/>And the great volumes of renowned Proteſtants, yea a whole ſtudy of them at once pronounced in mine eares a packe of Puritan Authours: Men comming to be made Miniſters, told they muſt hold their Tenets according to the times.</p>
            <p>And unleſſe the body of the Common wealth had been ſicke of convulſion fits, that men had ſmarted in their purſes, and bodily priviledges, God knowes how long the ſoule of the Church had laine ſpeechleſſe with unut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable ſorrow, without comforting compaſſions or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging permiſſions ſhewed unto her, that ſhee might ſpeake for her ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But ſaith Difficulty, why what is the matter? what great reformation yet wanting? have not we now gone fairely on, farre enough? let ut not pleaſe our braineſicke humours with changes.</p>
            <p>Hope replies that ſhe cannot but think that good chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges rung by Artizans are muſicall in judicious mens eares. That an ill Scholler is not ſaid to bee gone from his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and univerſity, till he be gone <hi>Cum pannis,</hi> with his cloathes; no more is inormitie gone from the univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of Eccleſiaſticalls, till it bee gone <hi>Cum pannis.</hi> Not a ragge of ſuperſtition left behind. In ſome Courts it is held that in ſome caſes a dogge keepers poſſeſſion. Sparkes left in aſhes ſometimes fire an houſe. And that it hath beene found by experience, that a doore of an houſe being left unbolted, and tapers or candles left in a readineſſe, they have beene eaſily lighted by pilferers to affright the inhabitants, and rob them. Chriſt at his paſſion rent the vaile of the Temple in twaine from top to bottome, to teach the Jewes to rend all their Iewiſh ceremonies. And when in thirtie or fortie yeares they would not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, the Lord ſent <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> who beate the Temple to peeces. Better that that Church had reformed with leſſe coſt then greater.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the valour of true hope, whereas falſe hope, is a faultering hope. To Sathan, ſinne, the world it will <hi>ſuccumbere. The hope of hippocrites periſh,</hi> wither at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:157041:19"/>blaſt. If it ſeeme to have any life for a time or ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle for life, it plainely deſires to feede on that which Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not nouriſh it to live in health. It lookes on examples, by ends, &amp;c. Sayth falſe Hope, Doe any of the rulers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in Chriſt? what if they doe not? But they doe. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus</hi> the Publican, <hi>Matthew</hi> the Centurion. What now, will the Jewes alſo believe? No. So in our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints. Doe any of the Fathers, ſay ſome, hold with you in your diſlikes? what if they doe not? Saint <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe will be followed no further then as hee followed Chriſt.<note place="margin">Juſtin. Mart. Concil. lat. Conc. Carth. Concil. Mil. Euſeb. Jren. Tertul. Greg. Naz. Conc. Carth. Con. Aquiſ. Origen. <hi>Every ono ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in his ſhare of oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition againſt the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of theſe times.</hi>
               </note> But the fathers are for us, as wee have in part ſhewed, and might name many more. What now, will ye be of our ſide now? No. Why then you do but poſe us with queſtions. But intend to oppoſe our judgements of truth. Now is no time nor place to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tie particulars, and thoſe Authors and made treatiſes, ſtore are in print.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Distinction.</hi> The Godly mans hope differs from worldly mens hope, in one maine thing (above the reſt) intimated in Text, Context, and Doctrine. Wee muſt then know what that is. And to ſpeake the beſt, or moderately of it: Their hope is ſuch as tends to ſecurity, carnality, formality, &amp;c. More diſtinctly and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The worldly man, or man of the world, perſonally for himſelfe hopes (as the Text Context and Doctrine intimate) that he need not bee ſo terrified from ſinne, with the conſideration of judgement to come, or with the word threatning it.<note place="margin">Deut. 29.19.</note> He hopes, as thoſe in <hi>Deut.</hi> and in the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 50.21. 2 Tim. 3.</note> that God is not ſo ſevere againſt ſinne. Hee hopes as they in Epiſtle to <hi>Tim.</hi> that a forme of godlineſſe without the comberance of the power, will ſerve the turne.<note place="margin">Apoc. 3. verſ. 1. verſe 17.</note> He hopes as <hi>Sardis,</hi> and <hi>Laodicea,</hi> that a name to live, and a lukewarme condition in religion, is a ſafe and a rich condition.</p>
            <p>Eccleſiaſtically concerning the Church his hope is,<note place="margin">verſe 8.</note> as <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> theirs in the Epiſtle to <hi>Colloſ.</hi> chap. 2. that the glory of the Churches religion &amp; worſhip conſiſts <hi>in ſubjectionto vaine</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/>
               <hi>deceipt &amp; tradition of men, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> rudiments of the world, &amp; ſhaddowes in a voluntary humility and worſhip of they ſee not what: in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:157041:19"/>to ordinances, tast not, touch not, handle not, in a ſhew of</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/>
               <hi>humilitie &amp; wiſedome in will-worſhip and neglect of the body. In meat and drinke, and holy dayes. In doctrines of men.</hi> In bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> cringings noddings, in bare prieſtly orders, in <hi>operibus</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/>
               <hi>operatis,</hi> or in whatſoever elſe humane deviſed thing mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a confuſed intention of blind devotion. Though by this poſition, that human honeſt intention of it ſelfe may deviſe formes of devotion, hath brought in all the Iudaiſme, Turciſme, and Papiſme that now peſter the Chriſtian world. This poore hope hopes that it is no ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition to fixe devotion upon the foreſaid or the like humble, ſeemingly harmeleſſe expreſſions, and geſtures, without a divine warrant. Though if any thing, that bee <hi>ſuperſtitio.</hi> And it hopes that the Pope is not the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt though that Tenet o're throwes the booke of the <hi>Revelation.</hi> He hopes that the ſame eccleſiaſticall offices, ceremonies and diſcipline, as are ſet up by the Pope, are no appendix, nor tayle of Antichriſt. And finally hee hopes that this hope is a good hope. Though a good hope is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of good things, not of evill.<note place="margin">Spes eſt tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum de bonis Fides de bonis &amp; malis.</note> And if it hope for things only good in appeareance, that hope is onely good in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareance.</p>
            <p>Whereas the hope of a Chriſtian (that wee may now ſee its difference) is of all good things, eſpecially ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and moſtly thoſe things that are moſt ſpirituall. The godly man for himſelfe hopes to attaine an height and eminency of comfort and conſcience, as the Apoſtle intimates in this chapter, and text, and doctrine. And therefore the godly man is afraid of the loweſt, meaneſt, and ſmalleſt ſinnes. In action, his heart ſmites him for vaineglorious numbring any outward confidences.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.10.</note> For taking any pride or putting the leaſt confidence in the creature. In words he feares a witty kind of jeſting,<note place="margin">Epheſ 4.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Which Ariſt. in his Eth. commends for a morall virtoe Pſal. 19.</note> if ſinfull, tending to the diſhonour of God, or wronging of his neighbour. In his thoughts hee feares any ſecret evill thoughts, yea ſo much as the filth of them. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence to him (though the Papiſts ſay tis no ſinne) is that which makes him cry out of his miſerableneſſe by
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:157041:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:157041:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:157041:21"/>reaſon of the <hi>body</hi> of ſinne,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> and ſo <hi>of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Church,<note place="margin">Exod. 10.26.</note> and her reformation; For the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of its reformation his hope is that not an hoofe of it ſhall be bated to the adverſarie. By the divided hoofe the Church was diſtinguiſhed,<note place="margin">This the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle alludeth to Gal. 2.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. verſe 14</note> as ſhe that had skill to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne between law &amp; Goſpel. His hope in that not aduſt, or ſmall ſtone of the reformation of the Church ſhall be troden underfoot and loſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102. And for the <hi>time,</hi> he hopes the time is come, when Gods peoples hearts are come to a full bent of prayer. As it is in that <hi>Pſalme,</hi> and other <hi>Pſalmes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſe 13. Pſal. 10.17.</note> And ſutably his deſire that the Church ſhould not give way, nor himſelfe approve of any thing contrary to reformation,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> not ſo much as for an houre. For he knowes that every duſt and every minute of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches liberty,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.5. Col 2.14.15.16.</note> coſt a precious drop of Chriſts blood. Things ſo ſadly bought ſhould not be loſt for a pipe or ſong.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Foundation.</hi> The ground of this hope is the promiſe. A good man is a great promiſe man, all for promiſes. In prayer, he lookes to the promiſe, <hi>Iacob</hi> in his prayer urged the promiſe.<note place="margin">Gen. 32.9.</note> In practiſe he lookes to the promiſe. Shall I go up? ſhall I conquer; ſaith <hi>David.</hi> In all hee lookes for a promiſe. In faith he looks to the promiſe; In hope he looks to the promiſe;<note place="margin">Acts 2.41.</note> ſo here. So that the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man is converſant in the promiſes; converted by the promiſes;<note place="margin">Acts. 2.</note> yea verſed and turned whetheſoever God will have him by the promiſe, as is abundantly ſhewed in the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> cha. 11. This therefore makes the hope of Gods Iſrael, in this land ſo quick, and lively, ſo cheerie and fixed on God, in his way, workes and meanes, and among the meanes, on you the Parliament, becauſe ſome words have fallen from Gods mouth, whereby wee have promiſes, to make this our land a land of promiſe. Now about, to be the promiſed time of the reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Churches in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome. Yea, &amp; in all divine probabilitie (ſo farre as we can ſee) you to be a promiſed people, to helpe in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Church in his Majeſties dominions. This, <hi>a promiſed land, i. e.</hi> one of the promiſed lands. For it is one of the ten homes, <hi>i. e.</hi> one of thoſe kingdomes of the ten
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:157041:21"/>dominions of the ten Kings of <hi>Europe,</hi> that having once hated &amp; oppoſed the whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſhall never be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to her, till ſhe be burnt with fire.<note place="margin">Apoc. 17. verſe 12. to the 17.</note> And that we may not feare &amp; doubt the fulfilling; it is added, that the word of the Lord ſhall be fulfilled. And that thoſe things that ſeeme to oppoſe, ſhall no longer oppoſe, till Gods word be fulfilled and to the end <hi>that all the words of God be fulfilled.</hi> But when that is done,<note place="margin">See <hi>Dent</hi> upon the <hi>Revelat.</hi>
               </note> Gods time is come (of which by &amp; by) he will no doubt put it in their hearts (let men buzze in their eares what they can) to fulfill that aforeſaid promiſe. This promiſe is ſo plainely interpreted by the Holy Ghoſt that it cannot be evaded, or eluded;<note place="margin">Revel. 17.12.</note> For it ſhewes that the ten hornes are ten Kings which formerly ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the beaſt, and loſt their regall power; but in Gods time ſhall be her deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Againe, ſome learned,<note place="margin">Parker on that place of <hi>Revel.</hi>
               </note> upon that <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.8. under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by ſunne, ſome eminent Church and ſtate (for ſo the Scripture ſometimes ſpeake) who having a viall of Antichriſts tyranny, oppreſſions, ſuperſtitions, &amp;c. pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon them, are provoked hereby to ſcorch <hi>men,</hi> all Antichriſts brood, and make them blaſpheme for their utter rejecting them.</p>
            <p>Take this for a cloſe, when Antichriſt is to come down, the Iſles ſhall fly away, rather affraid of her judgement, then in love with her ſinnes. <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This is <hi>the promiſed time;</hi> Now by this time its begun. For the period of the reigne and power of Antichriſt of <hi>Rome</hi> is but forty two monethes in all;<note place="margin">Apoc. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Apoc. 13.</note> even all the while the Temple is meaſured to be trampled, the woman flees into the wilderneſſe, and the faithfull witneſſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie in ſackcloth. Signes ſad enough, and plaine enough, that this while that Antichriſt reignes: eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeing the ſame time and beginning and length of time is preſcribed to all thoſe events. Theſe forty two moneths reckoning after the propheticall manner, uſuall in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies of this nature, a day for a yeare, Antichriſts period is about 1260. yeares; That is, from his evident riſe in the world, to his generall, and finall fall in the world, are
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:157041:22"/>ſo may yeares. For times a time and halfe a time ſignifies three yeares and an halfe. <hi>i. e.</hi> Forty two moneths ſolarie. <hi>i. e.</hi> of 30 dayes in a moneth, and Forty two moneths, of 30 dayes in a moneth, makes juſt 1260 dayes, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetically are 1260 yeares.</p>
            <p>From hence ſome of the moſt learned reckon thus, That ſeeing it is ſaid the whole bulke of the 42 moneths, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, the beaſt ſhall ſtill have ſome power to warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and kill the two witneſſes in ſackcloth; that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his power of 42 moneths is not to be accounted in a continued time. But that the beaſt was interrupted above five of thoſe moneths, whiles hee lay ſick of the deadly wound which was about 140 yeares. And now after the faithfull witneſſes had finiſhed their propheſies (but not their mourning and ſufferings) the beaſt redeemeth the 140. yeares, the five moneths hee was before let from his prey, and ſo to make up his full Forty two moneths. For for five moneths the woman, the temple, and the witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes alſo had a reſpit from his fierceneſſe. And ſo all in their ſeverall conditions the perſecutor and the perſecuted had an intermiſſion of like length, and ſo after their returne to their former condition to doe and to ſuffer, their 42. moneths run on and period together. Now by theſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned accompters ſhutt on the forty two moneths (conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuedly conſidered, not excepting out the five moneths ceſſation) to the apparent riſe of the Roman Antichriſt, apparent in all Hiſtories, Divine and Humane, to have been about 600 yeares after Chriſt, or therabouts, not very many over or under, by general agrement, and Antichriſt muſt needes be fully downe within two hundred yeares,<note place="margin">Very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly neere halfe the worke is done, by the ſtate prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome. And the third part neere at hand. <hi>Euſeb. Eccleſ. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> a few over or under. Meane while long before the worke muſt begin, and bee on foot, in doing. For a 200. yeares are but a ſmall time to pull him down in a hundred king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. Rome was not built in a day; nor will it be pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led downe in a prophetick day a yeare, or two. But if Antichriſt ariſe ſooner. 425. Celeſtinus then ſo much the ſooner. But reckon we with them more exactly, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept out the five moneths of ceſſation, out of the middle
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:157041:22"/>of the 42. And knit the five moneths, <hi>i.e.</hi> about 140.<note place="margin">If we ſhould advance the firſt riſe higher as ſome doe, as it preſently followeth here we need not wonder, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that text. 2 Theſ. 2.7.</note> yeares on to the end of the 42. moneths, that is 1260 yeares and adde to all 306. as the more exact account of Antichriſt beginning, and then he muſt needes be utterly throwne downe within 50 yeares hence. And therefore the worke muſt needes bee now on foot, to ſome good purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Others upon theſe principles lay downe by Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> long concluded with much comfort, that the time of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts fall ſhould beginne to good purpoſe 1639.<note place="margin">Napier. Dent</note> which they expreſſed in their bookes ſome 40. ſome 60. yeares ſince. And what God hath done from that yeare and ſo on, you have eyes and yeares to informe your ſelves, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps better then I.</p>
            <p>Adde to theſe things, touch the time,<note place="margin">Revel. 16.17.</note> that when the ſeventh Angell powred his viall on the ayre, it is ſaid <hi>it is done, i.e.</hi> Then preſently Babylon comes in remembrance to be judged; juſt then when vexation was powred upon the ſpirits of all carnall men (yet of the kingdome of the Prince of the ayre.) being gulled with the <hi>Agents</hi> of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, and ſtung with his tayle. And juſt thus alſo one of the ſeven Angels that had the vialls of the ſeven laſt plagues (likely he that had the ſeventh) came and ſhewed <hi>Ioh:</hi> the bride the lambs wife.<note place="margin">Though this place immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately meanes the Old Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt in the time of Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bees, yet it is the type of proportion of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments by Antichriſt, propheticall application comp. Dan. 8.13 with Apoc. 11.2. Dan. 12.7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poc. 12.14 and Dan. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21.12. with Apoc. 11.3. Daniel ſaith the power of the holy people ſhall be ſcattered, A time, times and halfe a time, three yeare and a halfe <hi>i.e.</hi> 1260. dayes. But if wee beginne the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt lower; From the ceaſing of the ſacrifice, and ſetting up abomination after that ſcattering. Then the dayes are 1290. But if any deſires to be ſo happy as to ſee not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the inchoation but alſo the augmentation of the Church, his new reformation, let him reckon upon 1335 dayes. <hi>i.e.</hi> yeares. So Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> had a double ſight of the new Church; firſt prepared Revel. 21.2. ſecondly conſummated verſe 9.
<list>
                     <item>Firſt, ſhe is a prepared bride.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, a married wife to Chriſt.</item>
                  </list>
               </note>
Cloſe we the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>time</hi> with propounding that <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. verſ. 7. verſe 11. verſ 13. to the conſideration of wiſe men.</p>
            <p>Laſty, for ought I can ſee <hi>you are the promiſed people,</hi> you the Parliament &amp; Parliaments of his Majeſties three king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes to be leaders &amp; examples to the Chriſtian world to pull downe that of Antichriſt that is yet ſtanding. Beſide that you are Gods gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt ſolemne ordinance for ſuch a deſigne, for nation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> exploits, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.1. You are the votes of all well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. You are the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Millions of prayers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ng cryes of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:157041:23"/>(no ſmall good ſigne, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17.) This further is to be conſidered, that they that are to meaſure out the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the city, the <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> of God, muſt be a man, yet an Angel, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.17. Humane yet divine, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime, in a higher degree of having ſtampt upon them the image of God in power and Majeſtie.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 14.17.</note> And a King (which is the chiefe of your intire body) is by the Scriptures ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med an Angel.<note place="margin">Revel. 21.8.12.</note> Yea ſometimes a collection of worthies in the Church is termed an Angel; as one Angel, for their divine unitie and amitie.<note place="margin">Revel. 21 5.6. See <hi>Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
               </note> Againe they that helpe in the reformation muſt bee thoſe that can make a decreed writing, can write ſtatutes.</p>
            <p>Finally, the northerne gates of the reformed Church, are ſet up <hi>with the firſt, Revel.</hi> 21.13. Abſolutely, firſt <hi>Ezech.</hi> 48.31. ſhould ſeeme the Northerne people of the Chriſtian world ſhall firſt, or with the firſt enter into the new reformation. They and the Eaſterne parts, the forefront. <hi>New England, Swedes, Danes,</hi> and our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes belonging to his Majeſtie.<note place="margin">Evill from the North. Ier. 4.6. Good from the North.</note> In ſtead of the former. <hi>Abs Aquilone malum,</hi> ſpoken in Scripture, and in our countrey proverbe (in another ſence) now it is <hi>Abs A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilone bonum.</hi> God will thus in mercy, recompence the evills of the Church, that the places of her troubles, ſhall be the beginning of her reformation.<note place="margin">Pſal 48.2.3. Iſa. 14 13.</note> As the temple was at the North ſide of <hi>Zion,</hi> King <hi>Davids</hi> palace, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his poſterity looked much on that Northerne tract. So Chriſt the Son of <hi>David</hi> on the North of the Church. Now all your hearts that are ballaſted with true hope up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the conſideration of the promiſes, will take more life, will be fed, and refreſhed with the promiſe, the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Cordiall and food of hope. You will heare the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſay oft in your eares, as God did oft, even foure
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:157041:23"/>times in one chapter, to <hi>Joſh. Be ſtrong,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 1.6.7.8.9.18.</note> 
               <hi>and of a good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage.</hi> And as you heard in the Morning, by another, out of 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.10. <hi>Be ſtrong and doe it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> But falſe hope, being unpropt by promiſe in tempeſtuous trials falle as the houſe on ſandy foundation. Falſe hope, produceth nothing but the water-bladders of phantaſie, they ſeeme as comely, as bigge, but they are as ſuddainly nothing, as they ſwelled to that ſeeming thing.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Dimenſion.</hi> The compaſſe and reach of true hope, <hi>Heaven and Earth.</hi> It gripes within its circle the publike good, the reſtauration of the Church like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payring <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and <hi>Ezra.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 10.2. Lam. 3.20.24. Pſal. 130.7.8.</note> Like lamenting condoling <hi>Ieremiah;</hi> like <hi>Pſalmodious,</hi> King <hi>David.</hi> Though true hope, bee not alwaies a ſtrong hope, at every minute, in every inch of the twiſting it is not alike big, yet it is a long hope every way large. And in the publike good, good men hope to finde their particular good.<note place="margin">Pſal. 132.</note> As <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> hoping to conquer the world, hoped no doubt to finde a meete palace for his owne habitation. And as ſounds come to the eare <hi>per circuitum,</hi> by ayrie waves and circles, and ſo the ſound is gathered into the eare <hi>per anfractus,</hi> by the windings therof; ſo true hope comes to the eare of the ſoule by the circulations of the generall promiſes, of the promiſes of the generall good of the Church, that in the midſt of that (and no otherwiſe) they ſhall find true comfort. This part or peece, the Saint hopes no otherwiſe to live and be ſafe, but in the wellfare of the <hi>whole.</hi> The whole being of relation, is to be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to another. Hope is relative to the promiſe (as wee ſaid before) and the Hoper is relative to the Church as a part to the whole; And therefore true hope cannot bee divided from its ſtrong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tye and ſubſiſtence with and upon the generall promiſe of the publik good. In ſo much that this genuine &amp; generous hope ſtrongly ſympathiſeth with the publike good,<note place="margin">Lam. 1.12. Amos 6. Pſal. 139.</note> with an Antipathie againſt the worlds Apathy and ſenceleſeneſſe of the common good. <hi>Is it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to you, all ye that paſſe by.</hi> And <hi>woe be to them, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not the afflictions of Ioſeph. Hate I not them O Lord that hate thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:157041:24"/>
            <p>On the contrary the worldly mans hope is a narrow hope. His way is the broade way. But his goodneſſe (even his ſeeming goodneſſe) is very narrow. No wider then his owne doore. No longer then the reach of his owne armes. Himſelfe is the center. All meanes to advance his owne ends, the circumference; like a jugler, he labours to conjure all into his owne circle; upon all elſe his hope lookes a ſquint, with a purblind eye that can ſee onely things cloſe to it ſelfe. He hopes to live to build, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, to injoy the world, what ever become of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good. The world can <hi>Glut it, and bowle it,</hi> at leaſt <hi>cant it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 6.</note> 
               <hi>and laze it,</hi> and never be troubled at the affliction of <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiſthly, <hi>Gradation,</hi> eminency or Exaltation of this pole ſtarre of hope. For a yet <hi>more new and righteous heaven and earth.</hi> The godly man hopes that the Church ſhall not alwaies live in a meere drudgery and ſtrugling to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine life and ſoule, and to attaine to no more, ſtill to live from hand to mouth, and gett no ſtocke of comfort afore hand. But as there are heroick morall, ſo heroick theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall virtues, among which faith and hope have their chiefe roomes.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.38.4.18. Hab. 3.17.18.19.</note> So that this heroick hope of the godly man is that though all the Church, in the true members, be new, a new creature, be righteous, is in a kingdom of heaven, <hi>i. e.</hi> in the Kingdom of grace: yet that there ſhall be a more abundant grace, and godlineſſe beſtowed, on the Church, ſhee ſhall be more heavenly, more new, more righteous. And that upon earth. Even the earth of the Church ſhould become more new. The earth ſhall bee as the Heavens, and the Heavens ſhall bee farre more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly.<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.26.</note> 
               <hi>The light of the moone ſhall be as the light of the ſunne. And the light of the ſunne ſhall be ſeven fold as the light of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven dayes, in the day that the Lord bindeth up the breach of his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ople, and healeth the ſtrok' of their wound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whiles the godly man primarily hopes thus for the advancement of the Church; he cannot but put in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by conſequence that hee hopes for himſelfe that hee ſhall he a Convert of the ſecond edition. Not a convert
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:157041:24"/>barely, and for want of Gods ſpeciall preſence and his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall acquaintance with God, to be as a beaſt ſometimes, in temptations eſpecially. This ſpeciall acquaintance with God (of which <hi>Iobs</hi> friends ſpake) is as a ſecond conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">Pſal. 73. Iob 22.21.</note> Such a man knowes more of God; ſuch a man is not contented to be new borne onely,<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.14. Iob 22.21.</note> and cry as an infant, and barely live; Be a generall honeſt man, ſalute God in morning in familie duties for all day. And not live particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with him all day after.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.164. Cant. 1.2.13. Cant 2.5.6.</note> But he muſt have intimate ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with God, eminent conſcience &amp; comfort. On contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Carnall Goſpellers, puſillanimous halfe profeſſers, are men of a weake ſpirit, of a dwinderling ſpirit. They think it is a jolly hope, a great ſtrength to hope the Church ſhall not be annihilated, totally eclipſed. A good hope to ſit downe and ſay it is well the Church is no worſe. Shee ſhall never be free from blemiſhes and therefore to what end ſhould I ſeeke for further reformation?</p>
            <p>And ſuch a man as this that is ſo low, and flat in his hope for the Church, he is as flat in his hope for himſelfe. He hopes if he can a little diſlike ſome groſſe vices in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſome inormous diſorders in the Church, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently this is converſion. That a good kind neighbour, a good common-wealteh man to maintaine the principles of the building (no matter for the wainſcot and trimming within,<note place="margin">verſe 13.</note> like the Kings daughter, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.) is preſently a good Chriſtian. He mindes not the example of <hi>Ioab,</hi> that was good in the former way, but little or nothing in the latter, that we can reade. <hi>Magiſtratus judicat virum.</hi> If a man hath any power of godlineſſe,<note place="margin">Exod. 32.26.27.18.</note> he will <hi>ſhew it on Gods ſide</hi> when hee is impowred with civill power, to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the power of godlineſſe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>David</hi> having danced before the Arke would not now bee daunted for his dauncing. Thus <hi>Joſhua Joſia, Hezech. Nehem. Ezra.</hi>
               </note> upon a lawfull call he will be as zealous as <hi>Phineas.</hi> Vpon an open contempt of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, he will anſwer for the honour of religion as <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Mich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l;</hi> upon a threatning of the true worſhip of God, and diſclaiming Idolatry, he will be as reſolute and as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen as <hi>Daniel.</hi> No flatteries of the Court, or feares of his enemies cruelties, cold make him to ſhut his windowes to true pietie, or open his mouth to Idolatry.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:157041:25"/>
            <p n="2">2. EXAMINATION, what is that promiſed new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie in the text and doctrine. And by the way let me tell you that now, before it be on earth, every man hath not a ſight ſtrong enough to ſee it. They have a falſe eye, as he that thought a field of thiſtles to bee a ſquadrant of pikemen, and armed men; So many feare the thiſtles of the Church, as edge-tooles, ſharpe ſwords to cut the hands of them that ſhall meddle with them;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cherubicall, et Serapbicall.</hi> Flying and flaming know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; zeale.</note> as before we ſhewed, that angelicall men, only meet to make an ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Church, exact walking, <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Enoch</hi> with God in thir perſons, the fit men to ſet up righteouſneſſe in their generations; ſo now that not every man is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſee abſent or afarre off this new eſtate. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>we</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle (not every one) <hi>looke for a new heaven, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo the Apoſtle Saint <hi>John</hi> in the 21. of the <hi>Rovelation,</hi> makes the ſame preface to his diſcourſe of this new eſtate, with ſhewing to whom this ſhall bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed aforehand to an angelicall man. A <hi>Iohn</hi> like man, acquainted with Gods ſpeciall manifeſtation. This the Scripture intimates every where. Both in the places al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged for the ſpeciall convert:<note place="margin">Iob 22.21. Pſal. 25.14.</note> and elſe where. As God drew neerer to the true plaine hearted <hi>Iacob</hi> then to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others. Shewd himſelfe more to tender conſcienced <hi>Ioſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ph,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.7.</note> then to all his brethren. More to <hi>David,</hi> then to many other good men of the ſame greatneſſe. In a word therefore,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45. <hi>Cant.</hi> in every chap.</note> the man that would have ſtill more cloſe union with Chriſt, ſhall ſee more of the glory of the Church. A man ſlacke in practice ſhall bee dimme in knowledge. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7, 8, 9. But whiles men are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciencious doing men, they ſhall bee more knowing men. <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.17. A moving hand ſtrikes fire, and cauſeth more light. Let mee appeale to men and Miniſters that lay ſtill foure and five yeares ſince, not ſtirring a finger for many truths, whether they have not ſeene more, ſince they have practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed more. All this I preface, being carried by the text, and commentary, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. that men may ſee that if they can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not foreſee, not withſtanding all diſcriptions, that new glorious Church, that the fault is in themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:157041:25"/>
            <p>Now to the uſe of Examination it ſelfe. This new glorious Church, if we goe to the promiſe intimated in Doctrine and Text, as thither we muſt goe, is to bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered under theſe three notions.</p>
            <p>This new Church is a new world.</p>
            <p>An holy Citie.</p>
            <p>An a dorned bride.</p>
            <p>So that though in the Text and Doctrine is expreſſed only a new world; yet in the promiſe is conſignified, and in the world is included the <hi>citie</hi> &amp; the <hi>perſons,</hi> the <hi>Bride,</hi> or it would be a ſtrange world that had neither of the other two in it.</p>
            <p>A NEW WORLD.</p>
            <p>The ſubſtance whereof are
<list>
                  <item>Heaven.</item>
                  <item>Earth.</item>
                  <item>Sea.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The qualities.
<list>
                  <item>Newneſſe.</item>
                  <item>Righteouſneſſe.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Subſtance.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sea. There S. <hi>Iohn</hi> begins firſt. Telling us there was none. <hi>i. e.</hi> No foggie, pudled, reſtleſſe ſea of corrupt Doctrine. And our Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter</hi> mentions not the ſea at all; therefore it was all one, as if hee had ſaid there was none. He would have it taken for granted: and yet the Church, hath a ſea, that is a pure ſea, of ſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. And therefore called a Sea of glaſſe, cleare as chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall. <hi>Revel.</hi> 4. <hi>Revel.</hi> 15. For as ſuch a ſea is moſt like to the ſhining heavens, and is the more excellent, ſtrained, clarified part of the earth, like as Diamonds, &amp;c. So the ſound doctrine of the Church, is the moſt excellent thing on earth, and moſt like to Heaven. But the Church (thus renewed) hath no watry puddle ſea of corrupt doctrine. At the mention whereof, Saint <hi>John</hi> beginnes, becauſe ſuch doctrines,<note place="margin">As good do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes, 2 Cor. 3. laſt ſo bad</note> ſuch All-things. State doctrines make timeſervers, phantaſtick, quidditative doctrines make proud factious, man advancing doctrines, the power of his will, the goodneſſe of his nature, the worth of his workes, make licentious livers, in confidence they can mend, and make God amends when they luſt. Sin-min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:157041:26"/>doctrines.<note place="margin">Socinianiſme is herein worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Arrianiſme Arrianiſme denies the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie of Chriſt. But yet makes him as ancient as the creation That God cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Chriſt firſt, and then by him all things. But Socinianiſme denies the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie of Chriſt, ſaying he is of no more anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity then his conception. <hi>Eſt ne Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus Deus? Imo, ſed non ſummus.</hi> So the Socin. Chate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme. Phil. 3.20. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Mat. 21.25. John 7.16. 2 Pet. 1.21.</note> The Pope is not <hi>The Antichriſt,</hi> neglect of the Lords day after publike duties, is no fin, &amp;c. Make a high way for the Popiſh Synagogues, and the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches to become one maſſe or lumpe of confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For this cauſe, this is laid firſt as a foundation of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that the Church hath no corrupt ſea of falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. No ſea of Rome; no Epiſcopall ſea, that ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit or permit, or ſhall be permitted to cauſe any tides of new Arrianiſme (<hi>i. e.</hi> Socinianiſme) or Pelagiamiſme, Semi-Pelagianiſme, Arrinianiſme advancing nature, or Papiſme, advancing ſuperſtition and workes. Obſerve that the new Heaven and new Earth hath no ſea, when new, <hi>i. e.</hi> when the power of the Church was reſtored to her ſelfe, all the Heavens &amp; the Earth called the Church, and in it wholly, was the power to ſiſt doctrines. No Churches ſo free from diverſities and corruptions of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines as the Churches of <hi>Holland, Geneva, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Heavens; as heare are many Heavens mentioned, ſo many things to be noted. But we can but name them, hardly, becauſe many.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Church is called <hi>Heaven;</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. becauſe ſhe is <hi>heavenly. Heavenly</hi> in her mind, &amp; converſation. Her whole politie or traffick is in heaven; her doctrine is from heaven, not from men. <hi>Heavenly,</hi> in her devotions. Vnto thee O Lord ſaith <hi>David</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.) will I lift up my ſoule. <hi>And thy will be done in earth as it is heaven, O our Father which art in Heaven. Heavenly</hi> in her intention, all ſhe doth, do tend to heaven, that ſhee may end in heaven.</item>
                  <item>2. Becauſe ſhee is <hi>Heavenlike.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.31. Revel. 4.10 11.</note> The whole platforme of her diſcipline and forme of worſhip, is according to the faſhion of Heaven. <hi>See you make all things according to the patterne ſhewed thee in the mount,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 8.5.</note> 
                     <hi>i. e. from heaven.</hi> When ſhe prayes in all things <hi>thy will be done in earth as it is in heaven;</hi> be ſure ſhe meanes chieftly in things of divine worſhip,<note place="margin">Malach. 4.2. Revel. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.1.</note> that all may bee as immediately from God, &amp; to God, as ſpiritual as may be. Shee is heavenlike for her light, heate, motion, influence, &amp;c. She hath the <hi>light</hi> of the ſunne. The glorie and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and doctrine of Chriſt. Shee hath at her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:157041:26"/>changes (when it pleaſeth God to cleare her nights) the <hi>light</hi> of the moone, outward comforts.<note place="margin">Revel. 12.1. Revel 1. Gen. 1.</note> She hath the light of the ſtarres, her Miniſters, and all their parts to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten her. Yea as God made the firſt heavens all a <hi>light</hi> body, before the ſeverall lights were made; &amp; ſince by the tranſlucidation of all the ſtarres no part of heaven is dark,<note place="margin">Ier 31.34.</note> So all the heaven of the new Church is full of light in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very member; every true member hath the ſpirit of illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and knowledge teaching them the inmoſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Scriptures, in all neceſſaries to ſalvation. So alſo hath the Church <hi>heate</hi> as well as light, as the light of the heavens, is the chariot to bring heat to, and in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunarie bodies here below, naturall and proper light, that is not borrowed, will not be ſeparated from heat. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the officers of the Church are called Angels. And they oft are called Seraphims, coales, for their zeale; and all the members of the Church are ſaid to <hi>ſeeth in ſpirit. i. e.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom 12.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> ſervent in zeale. Not like <hi>Sardis,</hi> nominall, or like <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea</hi> lukewarme in profeſſion. The Church alſo is full of motion like the Heavens. She hath her motion of <hi>trepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 2</note> She <hi>rejoyces in the Lord with trembling</hi> at his glorious greatneſſe, <hi>Shee ſerves him, but with holy feare;</hi> Shee hath her <hi>direct</hi> motion from eaſt to weſt, ſhe riſeth from death to life; ſhe growes in her graces; ſhe hath her ſublimities of heavenly raptures; and ſhe hath her <hi>retrograde</hi> moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; her returning motion. That when ſhee hath gone aſtray like a loſs ſheepe, ſhe repents <hi>and return's to the chiefe ſhepheard of her ſoule; ſhe returnes to her firſt husband.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. laſt.</note> Shee returnes to her father as the Prodigall. For her motion,<note place="margin">Hoſea 2.</note> her Miniſters are alſo called Angels, which are oft called Cherubims, <hi>i. e.</hi> wings. Finally,<note place="margin">Luke. 15.</note> the <hi>influence</hi> of the Church is hevenlike. That as the heavens proſper the earth, with ſpring and harveſt; ſo whoever receive and entertaine the Church, or its members, proſper for her ſake. <hi>Poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher</hi> by entertaining <hi>Ioſeph, Laban</hi> by entertaining <hi>Iacob,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 122.</note> 
                     <hi>Obed-Ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m</hi> by entertaining the <hi>Ark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, yea all that love and pray for Hieruſalem ſhall proſper.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Church called Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Becauſe as there is more heaven then earth; So
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:157041:27"/>there is (reckoning every way) ſpiritually more heaven then earth, more heavenlineſſe then earthlineſſe. <hi>i. e.</hi> In the Churches judgement, deſire, approbation, ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. She altogether eſteemes, approves, deſires all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things. And all earthlineſſe creepes in by ſtealth, with diſlike when diſcovered. The Church meddles with earthly things, but in an heavenly manner. Shee hath to doe with earthly things, but for a moment, but ſhee hath an eternall ſtate of glory in heaven. Finally the earth is of no uſe to her,<note place="margin">Luke 16.9.</note> but to further her towards he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ven. The unrighteous <hi>Mammon</hi> to <hi>be her friend;</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend her in her journey to heaven. Acenter is onely to draw a circle</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Church is called, or compared to heavens, in the plurall. And that becauſe there is a plurality of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things in the Church. Beſide that principally God is there <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. His doctrine is there. His worſhip is there, his graces there, in every true particular member. So that here is the heaven of the <hi>primum mobile,</hi> the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heaven, viz. Convertion by Gods grace. God is called by the heathen Philoſopher, the firſt mover, and he firſt moves by his grace. Here is the Chriſtalline heaven. The heaven of purity and ſanctitie of diſcipline, moving every thing orderly. Here are the heavens of the ſtarres of light, of which before. Yea here is, in the reformed Church The <hi>Caelum empyrium,</hi> the heavens of glory. For that ſanctification of mens perſons &amp; converſation is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a part of glory:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.29.30</note> and therefore in the chaine of mans ſalvation, the Apoſtle includes it and ſignifies it under the word glory. And all theſe heavens ſweetly move one under another, orderly and perpetually.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The order is obſervable, firſt the heavens are named, then ſecondly the earth, anſwerable to the order of the Creation, and the hiſtorie thereof. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1. <hi>In the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God created the heavens and the earth.</hi> If ever wee will have men reformed, we muſt get religion to be reformed. If ſalt ſhall looſe it favour, wherewith ſhall any thing bee ſalted? If ever wee will hope for a reformed common
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:157041:27"/>wealth, we muſt helpe forward the refortamion of the Church. The ſtandard muſt bee right, if you will have private men meaſure and deale right. If the vitall parts the braine, liver and heart be amiſſe, doe not miniſter right blood, ſpirits, and motion, the exterior limbes of the body cannot bee well. A ſad ſoule makes a ſickly man. Till <hi>Iacob</hi> reformed the Church in his family, caſting out the idolls, &amp;c. hee was never ſetled in the politie,<note place="margin">Gen. 31. Gen. 32. Gen. 33. Gen. 34. Gen. 35. ver. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> and worldly affaires of his familie, but hunted like a patridge, by <hi>Eſau,</hi> by <hi>Laban,</hi> by feare of Sechemits. But when the Idols were throwne out, and an alter built to the true God, and religion ſetled, then had he reſt, in <hi>Canaan.</hi> So when Church and common wealth grew to bigge for the ſhell of a particular houſe and familie, and ſo crept forth into a Kingdome, and Nation, when the whole Church in her generall worſhip was corrupted, the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth was vaſſaliſed, looke elſe over all the ſtorie of the Judges.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Earth. Heare is the laſt part of the new world. And though there is but one earth in the ſingular mentioned, yet here is more then one thing remarkeable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Church is called Earth, 1. To minde her of her impietie, mortalitie, and miſerie, while ſhee is on earth.<note place="margin">Ier.</note> That as the Prophet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> cryed out three times <hi>O earth, earth, earth,</hi> heare the word of the Lord, to put every man in the world in mind that he is earth in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, earth in his continuance, earth in his diſſoltuion. So it puts all the collective Church in mind, that whiles ſhe is on earth, ſhe hath ſome iniquitie, ſome ſinne, and ſo hath not here her ſpirituall perfection. That ſhe ſhall meete with outward miſeries (beſides inward agonies of minde and conſcience) and ſo ſhall have the <hi>Goſpel-affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.8.</note> Partake of the afflictions of Chriſt. That ſhee is mortall, ſhe muſt leave the earth at laſt, to get to heaven. Secondly, to minde her of her conſolation; that where ſhe hath beene wronged ſhee ſhall bee righted; ſhee hath beene tyranniſed over, on earth, and ſhee ſhall reigne on earth, <hi>Revel.</hi> 5.10. ſhe hath beene made old, in her face
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:157041:28"/>by teares, in her cloathes by ſuperſtition, and humane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions. And now ſhe ſhall bee made a new earth. All her particular members ſhall be new with grace, comfort, liberty of the Goſpel above all that formerly ſhee hath had, in quantitie, or qualitie, in one if not both. <hi>Rugaque in antiqua fronte ſenilis erat,</hi>—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am juvenilis erit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The earth is joyned to or with the heavens. Nay, it is placed in the middle of the round of the heavens; ſo that it cannot depart from its center point (when that may be) but unto the heavens.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> at the laſt day into glory.</note> So that all the particular mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are compaſſed about with heaven, influenced with the virtue of heaven. All of them are heaveniſed; and therefore all the members of the Church are called the new earth within the Orbes of theſe new heavens. The Church is the whole of the particular members. Not a Hierarchie, a Prelacie, or a Cleargie onely, are termed the Church But all that Chriſt redeemed, are called Chriſt body, <hi>i. e.</hi> his Church. A body muſt have all its varietie of members 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. It were monſtrous to ſee one all mouth or all eye, or all both. Miniſters can bee no more of the body of the Church, as a Church, but the eye and mouth of the Church, yea moreover; when the whole earth that is under heaven is put to ſignifie the Church, what leſſe can be underſtood, then that all the world ſhall be a Church, in the renewed condition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Sure not many, if any whole Kingdomes ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted:<note place="margin">Mat. 13. Out of our common pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er booke was expunged the faire interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the Communion, That the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts might not be offended Then. 2. The prayer againſt the Pope, that we might not offend his Clerge. 3. The prayer for the Kings poſteritie, as the electe poſteritie of an elected father. That the word elect might not offend the Arminians.</note> ſome ſprinklings of bran theremay be in the 3. <hi>peckes of meale</hi> of the Church, but not one or two of ſand, and the reſt of meale. The Proteſtant reformed Church ſhall no more ſhoot away themſelves to finde Papiſts, &amp;c. till they had almoſt loſt themſelves. Thus of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this new world. Heaven and Earth.</p>
            <p>Next of the qualities
<list>
                  <item>Newneſſe.</item>
                  <item>Righteouſneſſe.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:157041:28"/>
            <p>For both are to be referred both to Heaven and Earth. For it is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in which earth. But <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in which heaven and earth. As for the Sea, that is not mentioned unleſſe by way of excluſion. <hi>i. e.</hi> of the bad. As for the good, ye ſea of Chryſtall, the ſound doctrine; that cannot bee ſaid to be new, for it is <hi>ſemper cadem;</hi> alwaies the ſame, in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and meaning. Nor can it bee ſaid to have righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; for it is righteouſneſſe it ſelfe, and ſo <hi>non recipit magis &amp; minus,</hi> it is alwaies alike righteous. But the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens of a reformed worſhip, of worſhip made more ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, ſet more right, and the earth of men renewed in knowledge and grace, and made more righteous in life, may bee properly ſaid to be new heavens and new earth wherein dwells righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Theſe Heavens and Earth are ſaid to be <hi>New:</hi> firſt, to note that all old things are done away, <hi>Revel</hi> 21.4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.17. All things of the <hi>old</hi> Serpent, Idolatry,<note place="margin">Revel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.12.</note> ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on prophanneſſe, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.17. All the things of the old man. All his man inventions, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.9. All old things of the old ceremoniall law, of Judaiſme, much more of Hetheniſme, Papiſme, &amp;c. When God aboliſhed that he intended not, that his Church ſhould onely change their yoake and burthen. The whole diſpute of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in his Epiſtle to <hi>Galat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> tends this way. The intent of Chriſts comming was to this purpoſe.<note place="margin">Iohn <hi>i.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Law came by Moſes, but grace &amp; truth came by Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> 2 To note that this new ſtate of the Church muſt be as created, of nothing; So the promiſe. <hi>Jſa.</hi> 65.17. men are ſo wedded to their own pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſies, &amp; braine deviſed formes, ſo oppoſite by nature to ſpirituall worſhip, they themſelves being carnall, &amp; ſenſuall, that God muſt create all new, if he will have all new. And this he will do, as he did the world. He created it by the word, <hi>let there be; let it be ſo.</hi> So the Lord by the power of his word of his Goſpel will direct and draw his owne Church, and all the friends thereof to ſet up their new reformed worſhip, and to draw men to that new life and converſation in and towards the Church, which he calles here the new heavens, and the new earth.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:157041:29"/>The Lord will in ſpeciall manner inlighten, and inliven men, eſpecially Miniſters, to write and diſcover what is this new ſtate of the Church. Maſter <hi>Brightmar</hi> on <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9. <q>Thinkes that ſome holy man ſhall ſet forth a booke wherein he ſhall make it plaine to all the faithfull that the glorie and Majeſtie of this Church ſhall bee moſt divine and heavenly.</q> But more likely a collection of men, one or two out of every ſhire and County ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by authority, to meet and agree as one man, to draw nakedly and barely out of the Scriptures, thoſe cleare truths concerning this new ſtate, as will not indure any quiddities or querckes, and able to beare downe all contradictories oppoſed againſt them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe Heavens and Earth are ſaid to have righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe dwelling in them. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in which Heavens &amp; Earth dwells righteouſneſſe. Therefore all theſe righteouſneſſes dwell in the one or the other. Firſt the doctrine of truth &amp; righteouſneſſe, or right tenets. Not the doctrines of lies, legends, fables, flatteries. 2. The Doctrine of Chriſts righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, of juſtification by faith in him. As with much ſtruggle that doctrine was opened in the firſt founding of this new Church (though long &amp; much,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.3.</note> ſince that eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) ſo now it ſhall dwell, &amp; abide in the ſetled new eſtate, and never be baniſhed from its free hold. The doctrines of mans ability to keepe the law of juſtification by works, &amp;c ſhall have no more place.<note place="margin">2 Tit. 11.12.</note> Thirdly, the righteouſneſſe of piety, or godly converſation, every man ſhall have a care in his particular converſation, to practiſe righteouſneſſe. Fourthly the righteouſnes of amitie, &amp; charity ſhall dwell heare.<note place="margin">Iſa. 11.5.6.</note> Men ſhall not be wolves, tygers, &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of their brethren. Fiftly, here ſhall be the righteouſnes of Chriſts diſcipline. Chriſt himſelfe by the ſcepter of his mouth, not of mers braines, ſhall order, and diſpoſeall things;<note place="margin">Iſa. 11.3.4.5.</note> He ſhall ſo ſettle his Church, that the unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, not the righteous ſhall be ſmitten. And in what Churches doe all theſe righteouſneſſes more evidently dwell, then in thoſe that come neareſt to the Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call founding of Churches. See the Churches of <hi>Geneva,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:157041:29"/>Holland,</hi> &amp;c. No cryes there, by reaſon of perſecution. No cryings up there of human traditions.</p>
            <p>Thus of the new world.</p>
            <p>Next (that this might not ſeeme to be a world without inhabitants) the holy Ghoſt deſcribes the holy citie (which intimateth inhabitants) in which as we ſhall ſee in the laſt place dwells the adorned ſpouſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, therefore we come to the holy citie. Where we are to note
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Civitas,</hi> the Citizens.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bs,</hi> the Citie.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The citizens. And that theſe are here to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, both the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> intimateth in the text, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> for righteous men. And <hi>dwelling,</hi> which relatively inferrs inhabitants. As alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn. Revel.</hi> 21. both in calling the new Hieruſalem, the ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned bride. As alſo in ſaying, God ſhall dwell with men, in this holy citie, and no lyer, or abominable perſon ſhall enter therein.</p>
            <p>Of theſe citizens note the
<list>
                  <item>Subſtance. That is the ſocietie of them.</item>
                  <item>2. The quality. <hi>Holy.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſubſtance. <hi>i. e.</hi> Societie. Citizens conſtantly make a corporation, a well governed body (anſwerably, this citie called the holy citie,) which hath great varietie of officers, yet with great unity, amitie, and regularity. As things digeſted in a predicament, or table. No oppoſition betweene things ſubordinate; as we ſee in the wheeles of a clocke, that wheele next the poyſe, being the firſt mover, communicates motion to all the reſt. This corporation is governed by themſelves among themſelves; that is, according to their immediate particular lawes, and prive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges. The ſupreame magiſtrate runnes above them in the generall lawes for the whole kingdom. <hi>i. e.</hi> The King and Parliament, and Commonlawes are above them. But otherwiſe, their <hi>privilegia, i. e.</hi> their <hi>privata leges,</hi> their private lawes of their owne corporation, are managed by themſelves, among themſelves. The foundation of the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:157041:30"/>relation betweene each member of the corporation, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall; the generall, chooſe the particular. And the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular accepts the priviledge, and promiſeth faithfulneſſe and juſtice towards the generall. The communion that is amongſt them is ſuch that they admit into their ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie onely the good, and they eject the degenerating that turne bad.</p>
            <p>Juſt thus it is in the reformed Church of Chriſt; every congregation is as a particular corporation. Firſt, In it are all the ſorts of officers appointed by Chriſt; named often by Chriſt that the Church might not be ignorant. I ſay al the officers to continue to the end of the world. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. Teachers, and <hi>helpes</hi> in government. 1 <hi>Tit.</hi> 5. <hi>Elders or Biſhops in every citie.</hi> And <hi>Deacons</hi> two, beſides the elders. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.2. &amp;c. to the end of the 13. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.1. <hi>To all the Saints at Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippi with the Biſhops, and Deacons. Rom.</hi> 12.7.8. Are named, <hi>Teaching,</hi> and <hi>exhorting.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Let the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that rule well, be counted worthy of double honour, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally they that labour in the word and doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in and among them, with great unitie and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, the goverment of themſelves is by themſelves, touching all things done among them.<note place="margin">Mat 18.19. Obſerve well. Two or three cannot, may not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. So the text. But the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tell the Church</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) if more private admonition will not ſerve. And if the offender will not hearken to the <hi>Church,</hi> then let him bee excommunicated; which Church through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the New Teſtament, the holy Ghoſt by the Apoſtles explaines to be every particular congregation. So that from Chriſts time, downeward it was ſo to be taken. As the Church at <hi>Antioch, Acts</hi> 13.1. And when they had preached at <hi>Derbe, Lyſtra Iconi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> &amp; <hi>Antioch,</hi> they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned them Elders in every <hi>Church, Acts</hi> 14.23. And when he bad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anded at <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> and gone up and ſaluted the <hi>Church, Act.</hi> 18.22. He ſent to the <hi>Epheſus</hi> and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for the Elders of the <hi>Church, Acts</hi> 20.17. The <hi>Church</hi> at <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcillas</hi> houſe. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16 3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.19. So the <hi>Church</hi> at <hi>Philemons</hi> houſe. In hard times, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches were made up of religious families, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:157041:30"/>Chriſtians there abouts joyned to them in their mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. So <hi>Peter Martyr, Willet.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> at <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. The <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Aſia,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.19. which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> names, to the number of ſeven, <hi>Revel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">From the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time 300. yeares hot perſecution for the moſt part. So called by <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Virgil,</hi> and Hiſtorians, <hi>Hundred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie Cret.</hi> 1 Cor. 5.2.</note> 1 and 2 and 3 chap. Now it was much to have one congregation in a County, or citie. In <hi>Creet</hi> an hundred cities. And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Elders ordained in them all, for every particular congregation. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. Innumerable things and places more might be ſpoken for this acception, and meaning of the word and nature of a Church. But to returne to the point. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> is much troubled that the Church, the congregation at <hi>Corinth</hi> were ſo careleſs;e as that they had not mourned and removed the inceſtuous perſon. And the Apoſtle exhorts them (he being abſent.) I ſay <hi>exhorts</hi> them to excommunicate him. If the Apoſtle had beene a particular member of that congregation, he muſt have beene preſent. As in all inſtances naturall, civill, ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, the member acts in the body whiles united, no longer. But being a tranſcendent eye over all congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations (as we know he was an Apoſtle to all the world) though abſent, he exhorts them to act,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19. Act. 9.6.15. Act. 13.1.2.</note> and to doe their duties among themſelves, towards themſelves, in the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and relation they ſtood. So that ſtill the particular Church or congregation is ſubject to Chriſts Apoſtles, and all lawfull Synods orderly and lawfull gathered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures, in the nation where the Church hath her being, to rectifie them where they are wrong, to excite them when deficent. Or elſe they themſelves manage and act and officiate among themſelves, their particular diſcipline and priveledges pertaining to their particular Church.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The foundation of relation betweene the Church, and her lawfull officers, eſpecially Miniſters; is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, <hi>i. e.</hi> from mutuall union of affections ſolemly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwoven, and engaged &amp; twiſted together. The Church makes choiſe of her officers and Miniſters,<note place="margin">Act. 13.1.2.3. 1 Tim. 4.14. 2 Tim. 1.6.</note> and they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace their places, and flock. The Miniſter being ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>a Miniſter</hi> by the <hi>impoſition</hi> of hands of the Miniſters,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:157041:31"/>with prayer and faſting, the congregation chooſe him to be their Miniſter by the <hi>elevation</hi> of their hands.<note place="margin">A thema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> tendo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> pretenſá manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eligo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (in quit De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenis.) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> i. e. po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus (ublati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one manumte ſtabatur ſe babere decreta mea rata.</note> 
               <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 23. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> They gave their voyces to elect the Miniſter, by the elevation of their hands, or ſtretching forth their hands. And ſo the Miniſter is charged to looke to his flocke, as over which the holy Ghoſt had made him overſeer <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Miniſter is a Biſhop to his congregation. <hi>Act.</hi> 20. verſe 17. verſe 18. And the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are commanded to obey, and ſubmit to their Miniſter, as to him that ruleth over, and watcheth for their ſoules. Obſerve, over their ſoules, not bodies. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. And are ſaid to rule over them in the Lord to admoniſh (not over them as men, to conſtraine) and ſo to bee high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed of their flocke, for that worke. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.13.</p>
            <p>The neceſſity of this inward foundation and roote of relation in things of the moſt ſpirituall and ſtrongeſt combination, appeares by paralleling other relations though but in naturall or civill things. No husband, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, Maſter, will ſuffer a wife, child, or ſervant obtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on him, or on contrary; wife, child, or ſervant will admit of obtruded husbands, parents, maſters, as long as they be of age, and in their witts. How much leſſe ſhould obtruſion be in ſpiritualls. Yet if theſe obtruſions be exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, we ſee the unproſperous event betray the unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the attempt. There is no love, mutuall duty, or edification following. As wee ſee in all the obtruded offices in our Church, which ſhewes much irregularity in the Hierarchie; where many have the greateſt acts of power, yet not committed to them by the generall vote of the Church: and much diſorder in the ordinary miniſters, who ordinarily come in without the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo without the affections of their people.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, (touching the citie, or ſociety it ſelfe) note the perfection of their communion. They nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther admit, nor permit (if after admiſſion degenerated) him that is unworthy, neither officer, nor member of the aſſembly, congregation, or particular Church. See the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:157041:31"/>Churches, choice of an Apoſtle, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. of <hi>Deacons, Acts</hi> 6. See their rejection, and admiſſion of an unworthy member. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. of their acceptation and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of an unknowne, or doubtfull brother and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. <hi>Acts</hi> 9.26 27.28.29. &amp;c. to the end of 31.</p>
            <p>All which foure particulars diligently being obſerved in the reformed Churches of <hi>Geneva, Low Countries,</hi> &amp;c. how ſound in Doctrine, and holy in manners have they long time continued above other Churches: And ſo wee come to the qualities of this ſocietie. <hi>Holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This <hi>Civitas.</hi> This ſpirituall citie, is an holy one; which is expreſſed with an Emphaſis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>That citie, that ſame holy one.</hi> Should ſeeme that the old heavens, are uncleane in ſome meaſure. As it is ſaid in <hi>Iob.</hi> 15.15. The heavens were not cleane in Gods ſight. <hi>i. e.</hi> by reaſon of ſome uncleane (but in their firſt thoughts) in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, the lapſing Angells. <hi>Job</hi> 4.18. So the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, before renewed, although in compariſon with the dunghill of Hetheniſme, and the hell of Papiſme, it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a heaven, yet it is but as ſpotted, clowded heaven,<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.</note> in compariſon of a ſun-bright heaven. As an old garment, that may ſeeme very handſome, yet much fuller of duſt then a new one. <hi>Holineſſe becommeth Gods houſe, at all times,<note place="margin">Pſal. 93.5.</note> in all places:</hi> much more his faireſt houſe, newly repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. This new Church ſhall be ſo holy.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In regard of the more abundant and apparent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of that eſſentiall holineſſe. God in Chriſt; hee like as he made <hi>Moſes</hi> face ſhine,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.</note> ſhall make the Church ſhine. He like fire,<note place="margin">Revel. 1.</note> being among the golden Candleſtickes ſhall make them glare. When the Lord more ſpecially is in the Tabernacle, it is filled with his glory.<note place="margin">Exod. 40.34.</note> As it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied that the ſecond temple ſhould bee more glorious then the firſt, becauſe Chriſt ſhould preach in it, and bee perſonally preſent. <hi>Haggi.</hi> 2.9. So this new Church ſhould be more holy then the old, becauſe the God of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe ſhould he more ſpecially preſen there. This is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed verſe 3. of this 21 of <hi>Revel.</hi> And it is immediately annext to the ſpeech of the holineſſe of the new Church,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:157041:32"/>where alſo the reaſon is given why the Lord would bee more preſent in the Church thus renewed. viz. becauſe their was no more <hi>Sea, i. e.</hi> of corrupt doctrine, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men. Thoſe things that grieve God are remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The rule of holineſſe in the new Church, ſhould more rule and reigne. <hi>i. e.</hi> The Scriptures. When the Jewes ſhall come in, knowledge ſhall bee much more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed. Yea when the vaile of human traditions ſhall be removed, that the Church ſhall ſee that all in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God that is not evidently from the word of Chriſt, is not of Chriſts but of Antichriſt; then will the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale to her the full of the diſcipline of the Church. The full freedome of the Goſpel. The ſcales muſt firſt fall from Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> eyes, before he can ſee the Goſpel to preach it. Whiles our Church lay ſwadled and rocked in the unſetled cradle of humane inventions, the face-cloth of ignorance lay over the eyes, hundreds of truths lay hidden, which now are talked of diſtinctly in every ones mouth. So great an advantage of light doe they get, that turne their faces towards the Sun-riſing, and their backes upon the darke climates of the old heavens.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſcope, and intention of the Church ſhall be to advance holineſſe: not to make her ſelfe great in honour and dignity among men, but good with holineſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God. Not to inrich her ſelfe with worldly pompe, but with comfort and with conſcience, and the graces of the ſpirit. Her doctrine, her diſcipline, her forme of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. &amp;c. all ſpread the winges to hatch up holineſſe, even as Saint <hi>John</hi> was carried by the Angell,<note place="margin">Revel. 21.10.</note> willingly to ſee, what the Angell was eager to ſhew him, from the top of an high mountaine; touching the new ſtate of the holy citie: ſo ſure the new Church muſt looke, and aymes at holineſſe and newneſſe. And not onely aymes, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes all things to that purpoſe, but alſo hitts the white. For</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the new Church is holy in practiſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. Shee makes all her members, in the common
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:157041:32"/>eye and charity of men to bee holy, or elſe ſhee will not owne them for her children. By this generall frame of holineſſe in all her members, Miniſters, and people; ſhe becomes all glorious. For ſanctification is a kind, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of glorification.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> Therefore the Apoſtle wrappes it up in glorification, in reckoning all the linckes of the chaine of ſalvation.<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.</note> And the Church is ſaid by holineſſe to be all glorious within. The Church is all glorious by juſtification. But that is without her, and about her. She is wrapped in that, as in a garment. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.14. But ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is within her, as her proper qualitie, as a Church. Anſwerably Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> calles her holineſſe and <hi>lightſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> with knowledge and reformation,<note place="margin">Verſe 11.</note> her having of the glory of God. <hi>And that God was the light of the citie, and the nations that were ſaved ſhould walke in the light thereof.</hi> And for all things that are contrary to this new, holy,<note place="margin">Verſe 23.24.</note> and glorious eſtate ſhee caſt out, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. verſe 4. verſe 27.</p>
            <p>Fifthly and laſtly, holy in opinion and eſtimation. The Church ſhould be ſo really, and univerſally holy, making all her members at leaſt outwardly and probably, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace holineſſe; that holineſſe, ſhall be in faſhion, and ſo in eſtimation among men. It ſhall be no more a jeere, but a joy. As its ſaid by the Prophet, many ſhall take hold of one Jew, for religions ſake; ſo in this new Church much more ſhall men admire and eſteeme her for holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. So verſe 24. The Kings of the earth ſhall bring their glory to the Church. <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. verſe 24.</p>
            <p>And thus of the <hi>Civitas,</hi> the citie, the corporation of men.</p>
            <p>Next of the <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bs,</hi> the materiall citie of buildings, &amp;c. whereof note
<list>
                  <item>1. The forme, or faſhion.</item>
                  <item>2. The matter, or edifice.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The forme is conſiderable for two things
<list>
                  <item>1. Quantitie.</item>
                  <item>2. Figure.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:157041:33"/>
            <p n="1">1. Quantitie. As here the compellation or compariſon, Heavens ſignifies or intimates greatneſſe. (For what is of created things, <hi>extra calum ultimum,</hi> without and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the utmoſt heaven.) So the geometricall dimention there, in <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. delineated makes it, by ſome accompts, the greateſt citie that ever was. For if we reade the text, according to the ordinary reading,<note place="margin">Verſe 16.</note> 
               <hi>And hee meaſured the citie with a reede <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to the ſome of twelve thouſand furlones,</hi> and underſtand them in a more plaine and obvious ſence, of the compaſſe of the citie, that every ſide of the foure ſquare, was three thouſand furlongs, it will follow that this citie of the Church is twelve thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand round.<note place="margin">For every foure ſquare is one hundred times as much every way from ſide to ſide, as the length of that ſide is. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe a foure ſquare of 110. furlongs in each ſtraight line of the ſides of that ſquare. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s foure ſquare meaſured all along over-thwart from ſide to ſide was 3000 furlongs. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n King.</hi> So Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers.</note> And the whole plot of ground, from each ſide to each ſide, three hundred thouſand furlongs: which is beyond all other cities that ever wee reade of. For old Babylon the great was but a village in compariſon. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide of the ſquare thereof being but 120 furlongs, and ſo the whole plot of ground could be but foure thouſand furlongs. So <hi>Nineveh,</hi> was not comparable; for the text in the Prophet <hi>Ionah,</hi> 3 3. was o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> three dayes journey. <hi>i.e.</hi> (as the learned will have it) the walles were three dayes journey about. A dayes jurney being (according to the civill law) twenty miles. So that every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e, ſquare, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſide of the quade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>angle was 15. miles. <hi>i. e.</hi> 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> eight furlongs. <hi>i.e.</hi> 120 furlongs, and ſo was juſt of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of old <hi>Babylon</hi> in the Eaſt, and no more. Not <hi>is Babylon</hi> in the Weſt, <hi>Babylon</hi> the new, <hi>Rome</hi> comparable for at firſt it was but two miles in compaſſe; now at laſt, but a-leaven miles in compaſſe, and in the middle age thereof, but 50. in compaſſe; ſo that it fall 10 miles ſhort of the meaſure of the compaſſe of the walls of <hi>Nineve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if we reade as <hi>Arias</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. To the ſumme of furlongs 12. times 12. thouſand, Then the citie is 44. thouſand furlongs about, and the whole flore a 100 times more.</p>
            <p>And juſt as the ſtate of the new Church, under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or a citie is greater then other cities, ſo under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Church, greater then ever was any Church.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:157041:33"/>For the largeſt deſcription of the former Church, was but 144 thouſand long, and but 12. thouſand broad. But this renewed Church is by this laſt reading, 144.<note place="margin">Revel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> thouſand in the whole ſquare compaſſing it about. And by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer reading 12 thouſand in the whole ſquare bouting the city And the whole floore or breadth every way 300. thouſand meaſures. For it makes no matter what you call them whether furlongs or &amp;c. The bare numbers ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently report the proportions. And well may the new Churches proportion ſo exceed, ſeieng this makes one maine difference that ſhe ſhall be as wide as the world, (as wee ſaid before) nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e upon before the Lord leave the worke. And ſo ſhe ſhall be as great as good, <hi>i.e.</hi> greater, and better both, then ever any Church was.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Figure. Which is expreſſed, firſt more indefinitly. As if onely a ſquare upon a flat. <hi>i.e.</hi> ſquare in regard of length and breadth Secondly, more diſtinctly and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly that it was meaſured with a reede 12 thouſand fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, and the length, and breadth, and hight, were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall.</p>
            <p>Firſt, from the more indefinit expreſſion, obſerve that however it was a ſquare, whiles it is expreſſed under the notion of a citie. And the Church is a round, a round hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and a round earth, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es expreſſed under the notion of a world, the round; to ſignifie the laboriouſneſſe of the Church <hi>labor agricolae currit in orbe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.9.</note> the Church is Gods husbandry, her worke is never at an end. She muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually move here, <hi>propter qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tem,</hi> that ſhe may reſt whe ſhee is above the rowling heavens. To ſignifie that the Church thus renewed ſhall be capeable of all truthes, and conteine, and know and teach all truthes of doctrine, of diſcipline, of manners, and practiſe then too. As a circle (ſaith the Philoſopher) is the moſt capacious figure that is. The ſquare to ſignifie, that as according to the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher, a ſquare is the moſt ſetled and ſolid, faſt ſtanding figure, ſo the Church thus renewed &amp; refined in doctrine,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.26.</note> diſcipline, and manners ſhall never bee ſhaken any more, never altered in the ſubſtance of either, no not of her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:157041:34"/>that hath beene liable to ſo many changes, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in degrees, to as much better as may be.</p>
            <p>Secondly, from the more diſtinct expreſſion that the Church is as much in altitude, as latitude, as high as broad, this ſignifies that as the Church is growne eminent in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and high in heavenly mindedneſſe, ſo ſhee is ſeene of men, and eſteemed, and eſteemed and highly extolled with the reſpect ſhe hath from them. So that <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſalem is the praiſe of the whole earth,</hi> according to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Iſay</hi> 62.7. So that as King <hi>David</hi> preferred it above his chiefe joy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137 6. So all Kings ſhall bring their honour to it. <hi>Revel.</hi> 21 24. All ſhall as the Pſalmiſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to tell the towers thereof, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.12. <hi>i. e.</hi> joy to finde all perfect nothing miſſing. All ſhall lay downe all, forget all, even the cunning of their right hand, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the Church as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137. Chriſt in this his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſhall (as at the laſt day) be admired of all that beleive. 3 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10.</p>
            <p>Thus of the forme or faſhion.</p>
            <p>Next of the matter oredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice which includes the
<list>
                  <item>Walles.</item>
                  <item>Townes.</item>
                  <item>Streets<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>Temple, or publike place of worſhip.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The walles are confide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor their
<list>
                  <item>Situation.</item>
                  <item>Foundation.</item>
                  <item>Superſtruction.</item>
                  <item>Apertions.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt her ſituation,
<list>
                  <item>1. The walles are without the citie;</item>
                  <item>2. Containe all the citie.</item>
                  <item>3. Are conformable to the faſhion of the citie.</item>
               </list>
1 Without the citie, to ſignifie that no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyances, things, or perſons ſhould come neere the citie of the reformed Church;<note place="margin">Mat. 27.33.</note> without the walls are the dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hills without Hieruſalem, is <hi>Golgotha,</hi> the place of dead mens ſculls. The forme of execution of offenders, was to carry them out of the citie,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.12.</note> and ſo to puniſh them. The civill puniſhment carrying in it a character of the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all excommunication.<note place="margin">Phil. 3.2.</note> The Church is warned to <hi>beware
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:157041:34"/>of Dogges. i.e.</hi> Thoſe <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.6. For they are of the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion,</hi> and are <hi>evill doers</hi> (as the Apoſtle intimates) They have their dogges nature and skinne ſtill in and on, in heart and in life; for they are evill doers, biters, as well as barkers. And how ſhall the Church better beware of dogges, then as the houſe-holder, by ſhutting them out of doores. So the propheſie runnes,<note place="margin">Revel. 22.15.</note> 
               <hi>without there ſhall bee dogges;</hi> which are deſcribed by their dogge-trickes. Their mad <hi>ſorceries</hi> filthy <hi>lecheries,</hi> biting <hi>murthers,</hi> houling <hi>idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> &amp; falſe barking <hi>lyes.</hi> 2 The walles thus ſituated, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine all the whole citie, &amp; parts and perſons thereof; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude none of thoſe. To ſignifie, that Chriſt his Church, in no wiſe doth plucke up the wheate, in ſtead of tares. For ſhe ſees plainely the tares to bee tares,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> by their ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, before ſhe plucke at them. She remembers her Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours rule. That hee will in no wiſe caſt out him that commeth to him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.37. Thirdly, the walles ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to the citie, ſignifie the ſweet harmonie proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and conformitie that is betweene the Church and her diſcipline. She is not yoaked with a diſcipline that will wring her neck, &amp; gall her ſhoulders. Nor with ſuch a one as is like the hoope that the Juggler can creepe through.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.1. Compare ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.28.29.</note> Her diſcipline reacheth to all occaſions, cauſes, perſons, things. Shee makes not her meſhes ſo wide, as <hi>Actaeon.</hi> A hunter of wild beaſts, that catcheth only thoſe that would with open mouth devoure him; Nor doth ſhe as <hi>Vulcan</hi> make her net ſo ſubtile, that the ſimple naked ſoule may be catcht before it is aware. The Church hath from God her exact meaſure, how to knit her diſcipline, the pure golden meaſure of an unſtrretchable reede. <hi>i. e.</hi> The pure word of God.<note place="margin">Revel, 21.15.</note> 
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. Bleſſed are they that walke according <hi>to this Canon.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> marke the double emphaſis. This notable <hi>Cannon.</hi> This <hi>Canon</hi> of Chriſt. This <hi>Canon</hi> of the Scripture, or this <hi>Canon</hi> of wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as a new creature in and by Chriſt, according to the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Foundation. And this is of twelve precious ſtones. The naturall foundation (as of an houſe the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:157041:35"/>rocke,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.</note> gravell, or compacted clay) is onely one, and that rocke is Chriſt. But the Artificiall foundation (as of an houſe is the wall built within the ground) this is twelve fold, or many fold, conſiſting of the plurality, and variety of all the offices,<note place="margin">Theſe twelve ſtones were u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the old Teſtament as propheſies of the qualities &amp; conditions of the twelve Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and their tribes. And hereof the ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Miniſters buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ew Church on the doctrine of the Apoſtles.</note> miniſters, and their ſeverall gifts groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and guided by the doctrine of the Apoſtles. Small parts, or peeces, make not a foundation: many ranckes of ſtone make a foundation. Diſunion, or interruption of the continuation of a foundation is dangerous. The Church cannot conſiſt, with an <hi>index expurgatorius,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly beare inhibitions of reading theſe or thoſe bookes of Scripture, of preaching theſe or thoſe funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall doctrines or ſound truthes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Superſtruction; or raiſing the ſuperſtructure. And that is done up all of <hi>Iaſper,</hi> as the foundation was of 12. precious ſtones, whereof the firſt alſo, was a <hi>Iaſper</hi> as two other were, the <hi>Sardius,</hi> and <hi>Emerauld,</hi> which three ſtones are put to repreſent the Trinitie. <hi>Revel.</hi> 4. The green <hi>Iaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> the eternall Godhead, and Father, the redde <hi>Sardius</hi> the crucified Sonne Chriſt. The groeniſh Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e-bowlike emerauld,<note place="margin">As Gods bow in the clowd a token of an outward cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.14 15.</note> the <hi>proceeding</hi> Holy Ghoſt, the token of Gods covenant in the heart. Now that the wall mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> built up above the foundation, all of <hi>Iaſper,</hi> what can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, but that the Church muſt be ad of God, all accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scriptures. If men will build on the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not <hi>Iaſper,</hi> divine truths, but the hay and ſtubble of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man inventions, their worke ſhall bee burnt, if the men ſcape. <hi>Iaſper</hi> is hard and ſtrong to make the ſquared poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed face and ſuperficies of the wall againſt all waſhing; of floods or tempeſts; and precious, and ſound ſtuffe to fill up the wall betweene both ſurfaces or outſides of the wall. To ſignifie that the Church is as well all glorious within, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. That ſhe is ſtrong, ſo that the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt her.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18. 2 Tim. 1.7. Phil. 1.10. 2 Pet. 1.1.</note> That ſhe is ſincere, and ſound at heart. And ſo is, and muſt be, every one that is indeede and in truth a very member of the Church. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious within as well as without, with the precious graces of the ſpirit.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:157041:35"/>
            <p>Having thus touched the bulke of the ſignification of theſe ſtones, wee reſt chiefly therein. Some (as Maſter <hi>Brightman</hi>) put much in the order of theſe ſtones; as if therein were ſignified, the qualities of the ſeverall Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that ſhould follow, Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> time for the rearing of the Church. As the firſt ſtone <hi>Iaſper</hi> (uſed to ſignifie God, <hi>Revel.</hi> 4.) to ſignifie a Miniſtrie moſt like God (as the ſtone is of an heavenlike brightneſſe) ſtrong to beare the firſt difficult brunts of the Churches reformation. The ſecond, the <hi>Sapphir,</hi> glittering with golden pointes to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie a ſucceſſion of teachers excelling in ſome peculiar gifts to repayre the Churches wants in that age. The third, the chalcedonie, of a fierie brightneſſe, to ſignifie a third ſucceſſion of miniſters, abounding with holy zeale, for the further building up of the Church. And ſo of the reſt. But many will be ready to thinke theſe things to be niceties; and much more me to be over curious if I ſhould but intimate a proportion, betweene the <hi>Iaſper</hi> and the firſt reformers, <hi>Luther, Prague, Huſſe;</hi> of whoſe ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all magnanimitie hiſtories ſpeake aloud; as that <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid he would goe to the meeting to diſpute for the truth, though every tile of the houſe were a divell, or to that purpoſe. That infimite reproaches, the name of <hi>Hereſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archa,</hi> the putting on the head, the picture of the divell, the threats of torments, could not daunt the other two from the truth, nor from maintaining the truth; or if I ſhould whiſper a ſutableneſſe betweene the <hi>Saphier,</hi> and the next ſucceſſion of Miniſters, excelling with that gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of ſetling diſcipline, after <hi>Luthers</hi> ſpreading of doctrine. For which go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>den purpoſe is mentioned the golden reed, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. which was ſo well managed by <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l in, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>za, &amp;c.</hi> Or if I ſhould point at the zeal us Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of theſe laſt times, which with the light as well as the flame thereof were carried above others, to ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Churches reformation, by pen, by preaching, by hazarding, by ſuffering, that they anſwer to the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry chalcedony And likely enough that it would be thought as hyperphyſicall a quidditie, if I ſhould note that this
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:157041:36"/>third ſtone is a <hi>Northerne</hi> one,<note place="margin">Note that as the Northerne and Eaſterne gues are ſet up firſt, ſee before. So the firſt ſixe ſtones are Northerne and Eaſterne <hi>i. e.</hi> found in thoſe parts.</note> found and glaring in the <hi>northerne</hi> parts of the world, as Hiſtorians tell me. To leave men therefore free to their owne juſt thoughts; thus much I will be bold to ſet downe touching the application and order of the ſtones here. In the Old Teſtament the <hi>Iaſper</hi> was <hi>Benjamines</hi> ſtone, the <hi>Saphire Jſſachars,</hi> the <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonie Iudas.</hi> The <hi>Emerald Levics,</hi> &amp;c. And that theſe ſtones are here ſet down in the order of <hi>Morall</hi> or <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> conſideration, not of natural of the time of the birth of the Patriarches, not of civill conſiderations to reckon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mothers children by the mother ſeverally,<note place="margin">According to ſeverall cauſes and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they be ſeverally orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Exod. 1.2.3. compare Each. 28.13. Gen. 25. Gen. 29. Gen 30.</note> naming al one mothers children firſt, though not firſt borne before others named. The morall, or ſpirituall conſideration may be this, not to runne over all the twelve. <hi>Ruben</hi> his <hi>Sardius</hi> ſhould have beene firſt, but hee loſt the place by inceſt. <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.22. Then <hi>Ioſeph</hi> his <hi>Beryl</hi> ſhould have beene firſt, <hi>Ruben</hi> being depoſed, becauſe he was the firſt borne of the firſt betrothed mother <hi>Rachel.</hi> But he loſt it by <hi>Jeroboam</hi> comming out of his loynes, and ſetting up I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry. Therefore <hi>Bejamin</hi> his <hi>Iaſper</hi> is but put firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the remaining ſonne of the firſt wife in point of law. So that thoſe Miniſters that are ſcandalous, or ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laous, are no way fit to direct, or project in any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; any way to build the Church on her baſes or foundation. Secondly, is put <hi>Jſſachar</hi> his <hi>Saphir,</hi> which ſecond place <hi>Simeon</hi> his <hi>Topaz</hi> ſhould have had,<note place="margin">Gen. 34.</note> but being a man of a guilefull ſpirit, wonted to conſpiracies to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray a citie of Shechemites to death,<note place="margin">Gen. 37.</note> and was one of them that gave counſell to kill <hi>Ioſeph</hi> (for all were not of that minde; namely, <hi>Ruben</hi> and <hi>Iudah</hi> were not) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is put from his place and <hi>Iſachar</hi> the fift borne of the ſecond wife of <hi>Iacob,</hi> namely <hi>Leah</hi> is put ſecond, and hee the fift, is ſo put becauſe <hi>Rubens</hi> and <hi>Simeons</hi> faults you have heard already, and <hi>Levi</hi> and <hi>Iudah</hi> follow by and by with the reaſons. So that Miniſters that are trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous in doctrine or politie againſt Church or ſtate are not fit builders of the Church. Thirdly, is put <hi>Iudah</hi> his <hi>Chalcedony, Iudah</hi> is put after <hi>Iſachar,</hi> for that happily
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:157041:36"/>he might the ſitlyer intimate Chriſts outward meanneſſe in this world; and how he would not be a civill ruler over men, his errand being of another nature, a ſpirituall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatorſhip. But commended civill rule to the magiſtrate, ſubmitting to it himſelfe. But the moſt remarkable thing to bee noted is, that <hi>Levi</hi> by birth, ſhould have had his <hi>Smaragd</hi> or <hi>Emerauld</hi> put in the third place. But the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt <hi>S. Iohn</hi> puts <hi>Iudah</hi> here, and <hi>Levi</hi> next after, becauſe, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> diſputes to the Hebrewes, Chriſt a Prieſt for ever after the the order of <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> ſhould put down all Levitical prieſthood &amp; ceremonies, &amp; forme of worſhip. So that the Miniſters that cry out for &amp; in the behalfe of Prieſts, Ceremonies, Altars, Sacrifices, &amp;c. are not meet for the building of the Church. But on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. <hi>Benjamins,</hi> that will be Gods right hand, will be Gods agents &amp; inſtruments; &amp; their <hi>Iaſper,</hi> their parts &amp; prayers will helpe the woman, the Church in her hard travell, to be delivered;<note place="margin">So at <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</hi> See the Church his neede of helpe ſome times.</note> as the materiall <hi>Iaſper</hi> a naturall woman in naturall travell; <hi>Jſachars,</hi> that are the youngeſt ſonnes, little in their owne eyes, much in Gods; And are <hi>Sapphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall, i.e.</hi> heavenly (as is the propheſie and promiſe made to <hi>Jſachar, Iſa.</hi> 54.11.) which heavenlineſſe conteines as well a ſpirit of diſcerning and deſire of the new hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, as well as the higheſt heavens: and <hi>Iudah's</hi> that will deſirouſly advance Chriſt in all things, miniſtrie, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, forme of worſhip,<note place="margin">Iſa. 37.3.</note> and will oppoſe againſt the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite or contrary things to Chriſt, I ſay ſuch <hi>Benjamins, Iſachars,</hi> and <hi>Iudah's</hi> as theſe are fit for the building of the Church. I may not expatiate upon the reſt, to tell you <hi>Levi</hi> is put next to <hi>Iudah,</hi> and not ſo low as <hi>Simeon</hi> (with whom he ſinned in ſlaying the Sechemites) becauſe <hi>Levi</hi> after recovered his fall by ſlaying the idolaters, Exod. 32. Thereby to ſignifie here, that men that have ſhewed them-ſelves (as the <hi>Levites</hi> did when <hi>Moſes</hi> called. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.) have ſtood for right of doctrine, and a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſuch miniſters are fit for the building of the Church; I will not now deſcend to the reſt of the foundations. In a ſermon diſcourſe we can give but taſts of things.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:157041:37"/>
            <p>Fourthly, Apertions, <hi>i. e.</hi> Gates, or rather gate-waies, then gates. For they are alwaies opan: yet nevertheleſſe there are gates, and uſefully mentioned, both touching the <hi>time</hi> when they ſtood ſo alwaies open, viz. when all was new, no feare of old orders that any lying in the old <hi>Adams</hi> condition, might ruſh into the aſſemblyes of Chriſtians, and unto the Ordinances of Chriſt. And touching the <hi>nature,</hi> made of pearle. A ſhell of a fiſh ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated by the dew of heaven. Moſt fitly to ſignifie Chriſt, <hi>the loore and the way:</hi> yea the one &amp; only doore, becauſe they all of <hi>pearle,</hi> ſo generated, even as Chriſt was generated of the <hi>dew</hi> of heaven, <hi>i.e.</hi> The holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Compare Pſal 110. verſ. 3.</note> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowing <hi>Mary.</hi> And be ſure Chriſt will have a care of his Church, not to admit on his part, any polluted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. So that albeit it is neceſſarily noted that there were <hi>twelve</hi> gates in <hi>number</hi> (for all are but one, in kinde, or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) to note that Chriſt hath made way for all the twelve tribes of Iſrael; yet withall it is moſt appoſitly expreſſed, that the keepers were 12 Angells. <hi>i.e.</hi> The Angells of the Churches,<note place="margin">Revel. 21.12.</note> as called <hi>Revel</hi> 2.1. chap. 2. chap. 3. oft <hi>i.e.</hi> The faithful miniſters, to looke that no wicked Angels or men, that is falſe teachers, or foule practiſers enter in, &amp; ſet up a ſynagogue of Sathanneere Gods Church. So that by all this continuall opening of the gates, and yet continually watched, is ſignified that the Churches time of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhall not bee a time of open hoſtiltie from outward potent enemies; then the gates would bee ſhut; but if liable to any enemies, it will bee to the Hypocrites, that will ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne to come in, as if honeſt and when in, labour to diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>be, and defile. And therefore theſe are watched and examined by the Angells, upon any the leaſt ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: marke no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſumme of all (in relation to a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation) intended in theſe gates; That if there be not able and holy miniſters ſet in all the entrances of the Church, and they without flattery or iniquitie doe not bring in men into the Church, by Chriſt. Chriſt is not by them advanced in all things, and all things elſe, doctrines, cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, &amp;c. depoſed in compariſon of Chriſt and his
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:157041:37"/>doctrine and governement, &amp;c. then that is not the holy citie here ſpoken of, nor any part thereof.</p>
            <p>Thus of the walls of the citie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of the townes, places, or materiall parts of this citie. The whore of Babylon ſitteth upon ſeven hills, ſutable to her many abominations. But holy Ieruſalem the true worſhipper of God-trinitie in unitie, conſiſts chiefely but of three. <hi>i. e.</hi> Mount <hi>Aera</hi> the lower towne, for trading and honeſt walking in mens ſeverall callings. Mount <hi>Moriah,</hi> for the publike place of Gods worſhip. For there the temple ſtood. Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> for the place of publike juſtice and reliefe of the oppreſſed, for there was <hi>Davids</hi> throne. And all theſe firmely compacted, into one citie as in territories, ſo in ſpirituall, and civill agreement. All theſe are ſweetly ſung of in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 122. out feet ſhall ſtand <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> within thy <hi>gates O Ieruſalem,</hi> whether tribes goe up to the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>teſtimonie of Iſrael.</hi> For there are <hi>thrones</hi> of judgement; in   regard of all which now ſo harmoniouſly united,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iun.</hi> in Pſal. 122.</note> civilly and ſpiritually, it is called a compacted citie. <hi>i. e.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iunius</hi>) <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Before this theſe differed in ſtructure of townes; religion, and civil adminiſtration; for formerly there were three townes, and a twofold religion, and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, the one of the people of God, the other of the Jebuſites; but now all theſe, by all meanes compacted. In conjoyning of townes, in verſe three. In religion of minds ver. 4. And in adminiſtration of juſtice. ver. 5. In all which <hi>union,</hi> that <hi>union</hi> of <hi>three,</hi> of <hi>three</hi> into <hi>one,</hi> the King joyes, and the people joy, and all ſhall joy and proſper that can wiſh well to it. See the title of the <hi>Pſalme.</hi> And verſe 1. yea every verſe of the Pſalme. For what politicke man, if a juſt man, and a godly man will not joy when king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Churches are made as well ſtronger and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as well as greater: That quietneſſe, and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and Godlineſſe kiſſe one another. Thus ſhall be the reformed ſtate of the Church, of the new Jeruſalem. There ſhall be mountaines, thrones, ſtreets, &amp;c. all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted into one holy Hieruſalem,<note place="margin">See Revel. 21.</note> There ſhall be no <hi>crying</hi> through injuſtice; there ſhall ye no defilement through
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:157041:38"/>
               <hi>uncleaneſſe.</hi> And Kings ſhall take contentment therein; For they ſhall bring their glory and honour unto it. And then all may ſee the Church beginnes to bee new, when ſhe ſo ſhines, that princely glory admires her.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thing of this new citie are the ſtreets; which are ſaid to be of Gold. And their uſe is (we know) to bee an high way for the people. This is another character of the reformed Church, that the waies and converſation thereof in all her members, ſhall be firſt <hi>ſolid</hi> according to the truth of God; not quagmires, and hollow earth of human inventions; ſecondly <hi>pure,</hi> not onely from ſinne, but from ſcandalls, and appeareance of evill. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king heede of what is not of <hi>good report.</hi> And thirdly <hi>ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> As <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. carry out good examples to all. And ſtudying what hath praiſe and vertue in it. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Thing is the temple. For though it bee ſaid Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw no temple, yet hee ſaw that which was equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, yea farre more eminent in ſtead of the Temple. For the Lord God Almighty, and the lambe are the Temple. The Temple was but a type of Gods preſence in Chriſt; therefore removed, when God the Antitype comes. And not only the material Temple, as the walls and buildings were overturned by <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> betweene 30 or 40. yeares after Chriſt: but all the appendixes, all the ſhaddowes, yea all the darkeneſſe of thoſe ſhaddowes to be removed. <hi>i.e.</hi> All Jewiſh ceremonies and all Romiſh &amp; humane apiſh ceremonies that are the imitation of them. If the <hi>temple</hi> was to bee done away much more the move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>tabernacle.</hi> If divinely inſtituted Jewiſh ceremonies muſt be done away, though not changed for 3000 yeares, much more <hi>human,</hi> lyable to change every day, that like a tayler, the Church hath never her perfect trade of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, by reaſon of daily innovating faſhions. <hi>Ob. Revel.</hi> 21.3. It is ſaid the Tabernacle of God was with men. <hi>Sol.</hi> Not the Tabernacle of the congregation; But the Tabernacle of habitation: as tabernacles ſignified, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. So that tabernacle ſignifies in that place of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> only Gods dwelling among men, in a ſpeciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:157041:38"/>and in a ſpirituall manner, without the repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of himſelfe by a temple. All the repreſentation of him, was in the living <hi>Temple</hi> of Chriſts body, whiles on earth, which now is to be continued in the office of Chriſt, and the order appointed by Chriſt.<note place="margin">Chriſt reſignes not his office of mediator<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip till the end of the world. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this ſtate here deſcribed, cannot be that of glory. Iohn 4.24.</note> Therefore it is ſaid in the text of the <hi>Reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> That God and the Lambe was the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. <hi>i.e.</hi> God in Chriſt. The characters of the new Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem intended in all theſe are two.
<list>
                  <item>1 That ſhe is moſt ſpirituall, and immediate in all her worſhip. No temple but Chriſt. No ſacrifice but the Lambe Chriſt. No light in Temple, no lamp, or ſhine of the heavens, but Chriſt. They therefore are none of the new reformed Church; nor doe they act any part of the new reformed Church, that ſend the people about <hi>per ambages,</hi> by circuits the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt way about to God in worſhip by as many materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls, human formes, and dictated leſſons, to be learned by rote, and vayling her with as many ſhaddowes as may be: when as the worſhip, and the going to God under new ſtate of the Church ſhould be ſo immediate, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould come betweene, but the meere cloſe obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the rule of the Scripture.</item>
                  <item>2 The new Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem hath God more effectuall in the Church. He will bee better to her then the temple, or ſacrifice, or light, though of the Sunne. As he made the ſecond temple more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then the firſt by his preſence in it in Chriſt, ſo he will make the third more glorious then the ſecond, becauſe he himſelfe will be that temple. <hi>i.e.</hi> He will make the ſecond Hieruſalem more glorious then the firſt, becauſe hee will more manifeſt his efficacie, in the miniſtrie thereof. For if but the dawnings of the day, but the foundations of this new ſtate. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. were ſo efficacious, to convert ſuch multitudes at one Sermon, what then will bee the efficacie of the noon, and full perfection of it, ſo farre as is atteinable here.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And thus you have ſeene the holy citie, the holy temple, and the entrance. Now adviſe with <hi>Ezech.</hi> 8.9.10. chap. if in any Church the citie, <hi>i.e.</hi> the converſation and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous dealing of men, the threſhold. <hi>i.e.</hi> the entrance, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:157041:39"/>admiſſion of Miniſters and men, to the miniſterie, to the word and Sacraments; the Cherubims and Arke, <hi>i.e.</hi> the inmoſt parts of Gods houſe and worſhip be polluted in any Church? If ſo that Church is not yet made new. But if the inmoſt of Gods worſhip Holy Communion, and prayer be polluted,<note place="margin">Ezech 8 6 &amp; chap. 9.3.</note> 
               <hi>altered,</hi> and <hi>Altared,</hi> the Divine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging thereof, turned into human, then God will depart to the threſhold. If the threeſhold be polluted, all unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Miniſters be admitted to the miniſteriall function, all all unworthie perſons admitted as members of the Church, and ſo make linſy-woolſey, the aſſe is yoaked with the oxe,<note place="margin">Ezech. 11.23.</note> then God will depart to the middle of the citie, and if that be polluted, as formall worſhip, procre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ateth a profane converſation (witneſſe the Church of Rome) then the Lord will depart out of the citie unto the mountaine.<note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thus of the firſt and ſecond notion under which this new ſtate of the reformed Church is deſcribed.</p>
            <p>Now followes the third, <hi>i. e.</hi> A preparedly adorned Bride.</p>
            <p>We cannot here in the branch of an uſe, touch theſe ſeverally, as wee ſhall in another text. But in a ſhort and generall conſideration of them, wee may perceive the Church here to have two characters.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 A chaſt diſpoſition.</item>
               <item>2 Dutifull ſubjection.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt a chaſt diſpoſition, againſt all idolatrie. She uſeth no wanton kiſſing, or laſcivious talking, or imbracings of any idoll whatſoever; but holily deſirous to kiſle, talke of, embrace Chriſt, diſclaymes all falſe lovers; wantonly to talke of an Idoll, is unne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſarily to mention him. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.16.17. Thou ſhalt call me no more <hi>Baali,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ob.</hi> That ſignified as well <hi>my husband,</hi> as the word <hi>Iſhi. Sol.</hi> Becauſe the Idolater uſed the phraſe <hi>Baali.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the godly Jewiſh Church muſt not uſe that phraſe, <hi>ne nominans maritum cogitet idolum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>So S.</hi> Hierom.</note> leaſt whiles ſhe menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons God as a husband, ſhe thinke of an idoll. And <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.3.5. <hi>Let not covetuouſneſſe be once named among you, which
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:157041:39"/>is idolatrie.</hi> Wantonly to kiſſe an idoll, is to bow or cringe, or make a ſalutation towards it, though a man comes not neere it. <hi>Iob</hi> 31.26.27. <hi>If I beheld the Sunne when it ſhined, or the Moone walking in brightneſſe, and my heart hath beene ſecretly inticed, or my mouth hath kiſſed my hand.</hi> To imbrace an idoll, is to worſhip God, in, on, through or towards that Idoll. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Ephraim is joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto idolls let him alone.</hi> For ſtill they intended the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the true God. verſe 15. <hi>they ſweare the Lord liveth, whiles they tranſgreſſe at Gilgal, and Betharen,</hi> the houſe of idolatrous vanitie. Theſe three are more illuſtrated by their contraries. The true Church chaſtly <hi>talketh</hi> of Chriſt, when in word ſhee doth extoll and magnifie him. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10.11. &amp;c. Shee <hi>ſalutes</hi> Chriſt, and kiſſeth him, when ſhee applies her ſoule to the words of his mouth. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.2. This is called <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13.<note place="margin">Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Saluting the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. She imbraceth Chriſt, when ſhe chooſeth him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and forſaketh all oppoſites to him, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.7. <hi>I will goe and returne to my firſt husband, for then was it better with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi> But what is Idolatrie?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> It is
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>mente</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>ente</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>medio</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>modo</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
in
<list>
                  <item>minde.</item>
                  <item>matter.</item>
                  <item>meanes.</item>
                  <item>manner.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Mind,</hi> when a man hath vaine imaginations of the true God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21. or a meare imagination for a God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.4.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Thus</hi> Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, Aeolus, &amp;c.</note>.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Matter.</hi> When a creature is made a God. As the heathens gods; of which were 30. thouſand under <hi>Iupiter,</hi> whereof ſome were meerely imagined,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heſiod. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Perſius.</hi> The idolatry of theſe times.</note> as wee ſaid but now; others viſible creatures, as the Starres, beaſts, &amp;c. As the <hi>Egyptians</hi> adore Leekes, yeeles, garlick, onyons, &amp;c. <hi>porrum &amp; cape nefas violare &amp; frangere morſu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Meanes,</hi> when as one makes that to be the thing, in, on, through, by, towards, or before which a man will worſhip God, which God never appointed in his word
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:157041:40"/>the meane of his worſhip. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.5. They intend to worſhip the true God. But they erre <hi>in medio,</hi> in the meanes, in, through, &amp;c. which. Thus verſe 4. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle calls it idolatrie, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.7. So <hi>Acts</hi> 17.23. They intend to worſhip the ſame God that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would preach to them. But they erre in the meane, him they will worſhip, in, upon, or before an Altar. Therefore the Apoſtle chargeth them with ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Manner,</hi> when any worſhip for ſubſtance or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is without footing in the word of God. <hi>Colloſ.</hi> 2. See the whole chap. And <hi>Galat.</hi> 5. So <hi>Mercer</hi> (though a reader at <hi>Paris</hi>) ſaith on <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. <hi>omnis cultus ſine verbo dei eſt idolatria.</hi> All worſhip without footing in the word of God, is idolatrie.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Dutifull ſubjection, againſt all impietie, ſhe will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in diſcipline nor manners, be diſobedient to Chriſt. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.22, 23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Well you have told us a long ſtorie out of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> of a new reformed Church; but all thoſe things ſeeme to be like cobwebbs, too curious to hold, too prettie to bee potent, and prevalent; for you dreame not how dangerous this new reformation may be to the ſtate, and how prejudiciall to Kings and Princes. And therefore thoſe hopers, and hopes muſt reſt ſatisfied without thoſe hoped things, though now indeede they ſeeme to promiſe never to be ſatisfied in their mindes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and petitions without it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All theſe things are opportunely objected here becauſe they are cleared by Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> and ſo wee ſhall heare him free his owne propheſie from all objections, before we leave him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to the danger of <hi>State</hi> objected, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,
<list>
                  <item>1 the danger of condemnation, if any man ſhall bee <hi>fearefull</hi> regularly to reforme or practiſe reformation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the power, parts, and place God hath lawfully inpowered, and priviledged him withall, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.8. <hi>But the fearefull and unbeleevers, &amp;c. ſhall have their porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:157041:40"/>in the lake, &amp;c.</hi> Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> utters theſe words amidſt his propheſie of the new reformation. Therefore they muſt needs have ſome ſuch relation to non reformation.</item>
                  <item>2 He oppoſeth the dignitie, and commoditie of bringing to paſſe this new reformation. For ſaith Saint <hi>John,</hi> God will dwell there with men, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.3. Therefore no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience. For ſaith the 4 verſe. 1 God will wipe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all teares, by reaſon of antichriſtian Tyranny. 2 There ſhall be no mourning becauſe old things are done away. None ſhall have cauſe to complaine of the loſſe of them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to the pretended prejudice to <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> aſſures that there ſhall not be the leaſt ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe or conceipt of any ſuch thing ariſing in the minds of kings and princes when they ſee what that reformation is, but contrarie wiſe ſhall bring their honour to it, v. 24.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to the ſurmiſed vaineneſſe of hope of ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> promiſeth that the Saints hopes and deſires of this reformation ſhall be ſatisfied. Reade the 5, 6, 7. of that 21 chap of the <hi>Revelation.</hi> Therefore <hi>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai</hi> his ſpeech to <hi>Eſther</hi> muſt be remembred by all in whoſe hands God hath intruſted the power of reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>If thou altogether holdeſt thy peace at this time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſter 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>then ſhall</hi> the Churches <hi>enlargement, and deliverance</hi> ariſe <hi>from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place.</hi> I will not threaten that which followes to them that ſhall neglect to helpe in the Churches deliverance. <hi>But thou and thy fathers houſe ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi> I daily pray the contrary. But thoſe in place, may doe well to weigh thoſe words to preſerve them from careleſneſſe. And the words that follow with a litle change, to put them on to activeneſſe. <hi>And who knoweth whether you are come to</hi> have that authority in <hi>the kingdome for ſuch a time as this.</hi> And laſtly to conſider all theſe were ſpoken to a woman, whoſe power (more then by perſwaſion) what was it in compariſon of a Parliament of men, or corporations of magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>Thus of the uſe of examination. 3 Vſe is for <hi>Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> viz. to the world, to the Antipodes, the oppoſites to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:157041:41"/>the hoping Saints; being oppoſite not only in their hopes (if to be named hopes) but in their practiſe. The conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations to humble them, ariſing out of the doctrine are fowre. 1 Their hope doth not tend the right way; they doe not tend in their hope the right way. They doe not hope as men of hope; They doe not hope for the good of the Church as if they themſelves were of the Church. They hope not as if they and the Church had one Chriſt, one ſaith, one baptiſme, one hope of glory. And ſo they ſhew plainely that they are not of the common wealth of <hi>Iſrael. Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. And ſo not in ſtate of ſalvation. <hi>For there is no name given under heaven whereby we may be ſaved,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts</note> 
               <hi>but Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And <hi>extra eccleſiam nulla ſalus.</hi> Chriſt, ordinarily ſaves in and by the Church, <hi>i.e.</hi> men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the congregations, or aſſemblies of the Church are there called by the power of the word preached.<note place="margin">Rom. 19.</note> And beſides the loſſe of ſalvation, they ſhall not ſhare in the outward condition, comforts of the Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That having no newneſſe, no righteouſneſſe perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, whereby to deſire the newneſſe and righteous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the ſtate Eccleſiaſticall (for every habit of grace is <hi>truly</hi> deſired by the diſpoſitions of the ſame grace) they ſhall never enter heaven, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.5.1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The godly Church and her members ſhall bee hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, their condition ſhall bee joyfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, whiles the enemies that are oppoſite to them ſhall gnaſh their teeth, with tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of envie to ſee them proſper.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Church being renewed and rectified ſhall not be annihilated (as the wicked hoped): but ſhall indure to the worlds end, in a comfortable condition to trample and we are out their enemies as old ragges. The higheſt part of the wheele the wicked triumphing, ſhal feele the lower part of the wheele of the whole univerſe of men. <hi>i. e.</hi> the Church going over them, and preſſing them. Being thus turned by or upon the extree of Gods divine juſtice. That as the captivated King drawing the conquerors Chariot, looked oft behind him and ſaid (when he was asked the reaſon why he ſo oft looked backe) that he obſerved how
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:157041:41"/>that part of the wheele that was uppermoſt, ſuddainely was undermoſt; ſo may the Church ſee and ſay of the wheele of divine providence. And as that conquering monarch upon that ſpeech of his Kingly captive, left off to make ſo Royall a perſon his coach-horſe; ſo may the enemies of the Church be adviſed <hi>(if they would learne righteouſneſſe)</hi> to leave off their wheeling and rowling o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Church.<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.9.</note> For the wheele of the wicked ſhall goe over <hi>them. i. e.</hi> Them themſelves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.26. And the wicked will prove chaffe. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. They are old, they will weare out. Their very lamps of profeſſion will goe out. Thus of the uſe of humiliation.</p>
            <p>The fourth is of Conſolation. Let not drouping hearts ſinke within them, as if things ſhould never be better. Firſt minde the text and doctrine, that gives us item not to thinke as the world, not to be hopeleſſe as the world. It is the character of the wicked to have no hope of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches good; wee muſt bee contrary to them, 2 wee have a promiſe, therfore let us not caſt away our confidence. The word of Propheſie and promiſe <hi>a more ſure word.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19.</note> 3. All godly men for the generall (ſaith the Doctrine and Text) doe hope. <hi>Be</hi> we therefore, as well as profeſſe our ſelves like them. Say we to our ſoules;<note place="margin">Pſal. 43 5.</note> 
               <hi>why art thou caſt down O my ſoule? And why art thou diſquieted within me? Hope in God, for I ſhall yet praiſe him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fiſt and laſt uſe is for exhortation, that all godly men would bee men of hope, of a ſtrong hope to expect that which is promiſed in the text, and propounded in the doctrine, viz. thoſe new heavens, and new earth, &amp;c. Motives. 1 It is the clearing of your title;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Motive.</note> of your ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall eſtate, <hi>i.e.</hi> whether ye be godly &amp; ſhal have a ſhare in thoſe new heavens, &amp; new earth, &amp;c.<note place="margin">So the Philoſ. So the Poets. <hi>Homer calls minerva</hi> in commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mends <hi>Agamemnon</hi> for having an eye like <hi>Iupiter.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend a skie coloured eye, a heavenlike eye.</note> For he is the credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, &amp; hath right to the ſum, that hath the bond, &amp; looks for payment at the day. Beſides, nothing more diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers an excellent nature, then an excellent eye. And hope is the eye of the ſoule, yea of the grace of the ſoule, yea of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:157041:42"/>faith the principall grace of the ſoule. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. So that it being rightly fixed on God in his promiſes proves home to man his ſafe ſpirituall condition. So the <hi>Pſalmist. Lord I look as one of thine.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.15. <hi>mine eyes are ever towards the Lord.</hi> The ſpouſe alſo is ſaid to raviſh Chriſt with one of her eyes. <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.9. And the excellent Saints are like the beaſts <hi>Revel.</hi> 4. verſe 6. <hi>full of eyes, within, and before, and bee hind.</hi> Therfore upon this firſt motive let us labour to have this eye of hope, this expecting looking eye, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Church its proſpect, and her renovation its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Motive.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſerious hoping haſtens the performance of thing hoped for (for God muſt be pryed into, ey'd with hope; &amp; prayed unto as the challenger of the things hoped, before he will do any thing <hi>Ezek</hi> 36.37.<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.24. Pſal. 33.18.19.</note> So the Pſalmiſt. <hi>God ſhall ſtrengthen your heart all ye that hope in the Lord. The eye of the Lord is upon them that feare him, upon them that hope in his mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy, to deliver their ſoule from death, &amp; to keep them alive in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. Our ſoule waiteth for the Lord, he is our help &amp; our ſheild. The Lord taketh pleaſure in them that feare him: in them that hope in his mercy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 47.11.</note> When a creditor tells a debtor, that he lookes for his mony at his day, according to the debtors promiſe, the debtor will haſten to make ready his mony. So the Lord to performe his promiſe, when we by hope looke for it at the day. And therefore as the Lord is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by promiſe of mercy to become our debtor: ſo <hi>David</hi> challengeth him at his day. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.13. <hi>Ariſe O Lord, and have mercy upon Zion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.32.</note> 
               <hi>for the time to favour her, yea the ſet time is come.</hi> So when about the time ſet by God. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. The Saints <hi>Zechary, Elizabeth, Simeon, Anna, &amp;c.</hi> waited for the conſolation of Iſrael, then <hi>in due time</hi> God ſent his ſonne. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.6. And if hee hath given us his ſon how ſhal he not with him alſo freely give us all things.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Motive.</hi>
               </note> Moſt would have heaven, eſpecially if they could have heaven upon earth. Se here it is ſo promiſed, it &amp; ſo to be poſſeſſed. And <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. <hi>And haſt made us Kings and Prieſts unto our God, and we ſhall raigne on earth.</hi> And this heaven beneath is the earneſt of heaven above.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:157041:42"/>Therefore, ſhall we not hope for it? In paſſion wee wiſh our ſelves in heaven; much more ſhould wee on groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded conſideration. And if to be in the houſe, then to be in the porch that neceſſarily leadeth to it for all of that age; and for our poſterity if not for us. We are ſo whee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led about with heaven, that we cannot (one would think) forget it, ſure enough not get out of it, fall through it. So that if men periſh it muſt be by burying themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live in the center by earthlineſſe, and emptineſſe of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly hope. 4. Wee mightily affect newalties.<note place="margin">4 <hi>Motive.</hi>
               </note> As one once, ſo we make it our Motto <hi>Nil jucundum, niſi quod re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit varietas.</hi> Nothing hath any jucunditie in't, but onely there is a refreſhment from varietie. Loe here is a new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all things. The Aſtronomers mightily gaze after new ſtarres (though but ſo, in their ſildome appearance) The husbandman mightily joyes in a new ſoyle, new broken earth. How much more ſhould we deſire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and hope for a new ſpirituall heaven and earth, upon earh, when ſo firmely propheſied, and promiſed. 5 We mightily cry out againſt unrighteouſneſſe, and ſigh for right to take place. And wee are quieted and comforted if a Judge promiſeth us, that he will doe us right. How much more ſhould we deſire and hope on God (that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lie, nor bee weake or unwilling to doe good) to bee eaſed of the unrighteouſneſſe that oppreſſeth the Church.</p>
            <p>Meanes. 1. Conſider we have a promiſe,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Meanes.</hi>
               </note> under Gods hand; yea many promiſes. By the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> of which a fore. Of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> here taking up thoſe promiſes, and avouching them: yea ſince Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> wee have a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall promiſe by Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in the <hi>Revelat.</hi> 21. yea the whole book of the <hi>Revelat.</hi> tends to this as one whole Syſtem of promiſes. Now God cannot lye. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1. He hath ſworne that in Iſaack, that is in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Gen 22.16.17.</note> all the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall be bleſſed (this includes all things) God cannot be perjured.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is God that makes theſe promiſes long ſince. Above 16 hundred yeares ſince, the laſt of them,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:157041:43"/>And much more, the formoſt of them, and as all other his promiſes have not failed. The nations are bleſſed in Chriſt comming.<note place="margin">Ioſh 21.45.</note> The reſt of <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> propheſies are ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled touching the Iſraelites captivitie in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and their returne. The reſt of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> propheſies are ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled. He ſuffered Martyrdom as he foretold. All the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> propheſies are fulfililed in the former viols and ſeales, to theſe times. And now if ever, we ſee a dawning of the propheſie of the text, and the promiſed mentioned in the text, why ſhould we not beleeve. Above all in promiſe keeping doth the Lord glory to ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a <hi>Iehovah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Exod. 6.3.</note> conſider theſe impleaded promiſes. Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> hath impleaded the promiſes in <hi>Iſai.</hi> Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the types and viſions in <hi>Ezech.</hi> And the Saints eſpecially with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe few yeares, have mightily challenged God on theſe promiſes that ſpeake of a new heaven, &amp;c. uttered by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> Therefore make ſure, God for his honour, will not have ſo many eyes upon him, and fayle in his promiſes ſo divulged, and canva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 1. This is a difficult buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hope is of ſuch things, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.8. creation is a about ſuch things,<note place="margin">Potentia irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtentiae.</note> the promiſe ſaith theſe new heavens &amp;c. ſhall be <hi>created.</hi> In creation, the creature cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. Remember the Atoms, and hopeleſſe beginnings of <hi>Luthers</hi> time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 2. God uſeth meanes; we ſee none competent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hope that is ſeene is no hope, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>Creation</hi> is without meanes. Immediate creation, abſolutely of nothing. So the Chaos. Mediate as of <hi>Adam,</hi> of that which was as good as nothing. Nor can the object bee ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly intimated to bee a meanes in creation, which is meerely paſſive, but God preſents to us many meanes, which we ſee not, eſpecially under the relation of meanes. As the enemies owne plotts are oftentimes made meanes. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.16. <hi>Pro.</hi> 11.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 3. But oft, and by fits, things run croſſe, and contrary.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:157041:43"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Creation is out of contraries, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. And ſo is the creation of the Churches reformation. Remember Iſraels deliverance out of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 4. But ſtill the Churches enemies are many and ſtrong, and the Church is weake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Creation is invinciable. It turnes water into wine. God could make any thing of the beautifull world out of the Chaos.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 5. We are unworthy, many unworthy perſons, and things yet in the Church, and not only here left, but here loved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> God tells Iſrael hee would deliver them for his owne ſake, for his <hi>name, Ezech.</hi> 36.21. <hi>He will be jealous for his name, Ezech.</hi> 39.25. And not for their ſakes, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 36.22. There is no worthineſſe in the matter of creation. God made us his new creation in Chriſt when wee were enemies, much more therfore being now reconciled, ſhall we be delivered from wrath <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10.</p>
            <p>To wind up all (for it is high time.) God hath ſaid, and ſaid, it ſhall be; trouble wee not our heads, when, how, wherewith. Trouble wee (if we will doe any thing) our hearts to bring them to beleeve. God is ſo ſweet in his mercy, ſo ſure in his truth, ſo ſupreme in his power, that as in prayer we cannot be denyed,<note place="margin">Luke 18. v. 1. ver. 7.</note> unleſſe wee will bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied; ſo there is no reaſon why we ſhould not beleeve and hope but onely that we will not. Wherefore let us fall ſhort of nothing for want of a doing, praying living ſaith and hope put forth we our hope upon the promiſe, with an holy proteſtation of minde, oft reſolved,<note place="margin">Ezech. 33.11.</note> and renewed, according to the expreſſion of the text. <hi>Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> notwithſtanding all difficulties and doubts, wee according <hi>to his promiſe looke for new heavens and a new earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſſe;</hi> and ſtill at the cloſe let our owne hearts anſwer, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
